<section xml:id="oneD-Position-Velocity-Acceleration-Summary"><title> Position, Velocity, Acceleration Summary </title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			We have covered a lot of ground and it is easy to get overwhelmed. In the end, we are basically, trying to understand the rate of change of position <m> x </m> and rate of change of velocity <m>v_x</m>.
			<xref ref="fig-x-v-a-relations"/> summarizes how to go from <m> x </m> to <m> v_x</m> to <m> a_x </m>, and in the reverse order, from <m> a_x </m> to <m> v_x</m> to <m> x </m>.

		</p>
		<figure xml:id="fig-x-v-a-relations">
			<caption>
				Relations in one-dimensional motion. We compute rate of change from the slopes of tangents of the quantity, we are finding the rate of, and to compute the change in a quantity, we find area under the curve of rate curve. For instance, to get the rate of change of <m> x</m>, i.e., to compute <m> v_x</m>, we find the slope of the tangent to the plot of <m> x </m> versus <m> t </m>, which is equivalent to taking the derivative of<m>x(t)</m>, and to compute <m> a_x</m> from <m>v_x</m>, we find the slope of the tangent to the plot of <m> v_x </m> versus <m> t </m>, which is equivalent to taking the derivative of<m>v_x(t)</m>. Going in the reverse order, to compute the change in <m> x </m> from <m> v_x </m> versus <m> t </m> plot, we compute the area under/over the curve, and similarly, to compute the change in <m> v_x </m> from <m> a_x </m> versus <m> t </m> plot, we compute the area under/over the curve of <m> a_x</m>. The area under the curve is another way of computing the integrals.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/one-dim-motion/x-v-a-relations.png" width="65%"/>

		</figure>
		
	</introduction>
	<subsection><title> (Calculus) Position, Velocity, Acceleration Summary</title>

		The same schematic picture in Calculus language is shown in <xref ref="fig-x-v-a-relations-calculus"/>.
		
		<figure xml:id="fig-x-v-a-relations-calculus">
			<caption>
				Schematics of relation between <m>x</m>, corresponding velocity <m>v_x</m> and acceleration <m>a_x</m>.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/one-dim-motion/x-v-a-relations-calculus.png" width="70%"/>
		</figure>
		
	</subsection>

</section>