<section xml:id="Capacitor-with-a-Dielectric"><title> Capacitor with a Dielectric </title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			A common way to increase the capacitance of a capacitor is to fill the space between the plates with a dielectric such as mica.  With the reduced electric field between the plates the potential difference between the plates would be less.  Therefore, you can put larger amount of charge on the plates for the same potential difference.
		</p>
		<p>
			Let <m>C_0</m> be the capacitance with nothing between the plates and <m>C</m> the capacitance, when the space is filled with a dielectric of dielectric constant <m>\epsilon_r</m>. The two will be related by
			<me>
				C = \epsilon_r C_0,
			</me>
			Usually mica, cardboard, or paper is put between the plates of a capacitor to increase the capacitance.   
		</p>
	</introduction>
	<subsection><title>Capacitance of a Parallel Plate Capacitor with Dielectric </title>
		<p>
			Previously, we have worked out the formula for the electric field in a parallel plate capacitor of area <m>A</m> and separation <m>d</m> without a dielectric.  We had found that, if the plates have charges <m>\pm Q</m> on them, then the magnitude of the electric field between plates is uniform with the magnitude given by
			<me>
				E_0 = \dfrac{Q/A}{\epsilon_0}, \ \ \ \text{(No dielectric.)}
			</me>
			Since this field is constant, multiplying this by the separation distance <m>d</m> gives the potential difference, which we will denote by <m>\Delta \phi_0</m>.
			<me>
				\Delta \phi_0 = \dfrac{Qd}{\epsilon_0 A}.
			</me>
			The ratio of charge <m>Q</m> to the voltage difference <m>\Delta \phi_0</m> is the capacitance <m>C_0</m> of the capacitor.
			<me>
				C_0 = \dfrac{\epsilon_0 A}{d}.
			</me>
			With a dielectric between the plates the magnitude of the electric field between the plates will be reduced by a factor of the dielectric constant, <m>\epsilon_r</m>.  
			<me>
				E = \frac{E_0}{\epsilon_r}, \ \ \ \text{(with dielectric.)}
			</me>
			Therefore, potential difference <m>\Delta \phi</m> with dielectric between the plates will be less.
			<me>
				\Delta \phi = \dfrac{V_0}{\epsilon_r}  = \dfrac{Qd}{\epsilon_r\epsilon_0 A}.
			</me>
			This gives the capacitance <m> C</m> for the capacitor with the dielectric in terms of the capacitance <m> C_0</m> as
			<men>
			 	C = \frac{Q}{V} = \frac{\epsilon_r\epsilon_0 A}{d} = \epsilon_r C_0.
			</men>
		</p>
	</subsection>





 










</section>