<section><title> Thermodynamic Systems </title>

	<subsection> <title>Thermodynamic Equilibrium </title>

			<p>
			In thermodynamics we study phenomena associated with heating and cooling. The mechanical view would require understanding these phenomena from the motions of each atom and molecule in the body. The branch of physics, called <term> statistical mechanics</term>, attempts to obtain explanations of thermal phenomena from the average behavior of large number of constituent particles. 
		</p>
		<p>
			In thermodynamics, on the other hand, we rely on laws/results obtained from observations or experiments, which we apply to understand how a thermodynamic state changes with environment. The fundamental difference between the thermodynamics way and the mechanics way is how we specify a state. Just as in the mechanical system, the interesting part of the study is the study of change of state because that is how we interact with the system.
		</p>
		<p>
			In thermodynamics, the state is specified by macroscopic observable properties, such as pressure, temperature, volume, magnetization, etc. Clearly, the list of properties depend on particular body we are studying.
			Furthermore, determining macroscopic observables requires waiting till the values have stabilized and the system has reached, what is called, <term>  thermodynamic equilibrium</term>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			Whenever you place your system in a new environment, the properties take time to stabilize. You might say that we are unable to specify the thermodynamic state unless the thermodynamic properties have stopped changing. For instance, when you heat some water in a beaker, the bottom part is at a higher temperture than the top part, and hence, you cannot give a unique answer to the question: what is the temperature of water in the beaker. But, if you stop heating and stir the heated water well, you will get the same reading of the temperature throughout, which you can use to specify the state.
		</p>
	</subsection>


	<subsection><title>Isolated, Closed, and Open Systems</title>

		<p>
			Every system in thermodynamics can be classified as isolated, closed, or open.
			<ol>
				<li><alert> Isolated System.</alert>  When a system is completely separated from the rest of the universe such that it does not interact with the outside world in any way, then from mechanics we know that the energy, momentum and angular momentum of the system will not change with time. Such systems do not exchange energy, momentum or angular momentum with any other object in the universe. The entire universe is, of course, an isolated system.</li>
				<li><alert> Closed System.</alert> A closed system is not completely isolated from the rest of the universe. A closed system is restricted to have a constant mass.  But, a closed system can interact with the external world. Suppose you place some water in a closed container and heat the container.  The energy of the water in the container will go up even though the amount of water remains the same.  The water in the closed container is an example of a closed system. Most of the examples in this book will be presented for closed systems.</li>
				<li><alert> Open System.</alert> An open system can exchange even matter with the environment. This is most general type of system.  Your body, for instance, is an open thermodynamic system since the chemical content of your body is constantly changing.  </li>
			</ol>
		</p>

		<p>

			You can start from an isolated system and divide up the space into smaller parts and obtain open or closed systems which would be the sub-systems of the larger isolated system. The conservation laws of physics, such as the conservation of energy, the conservation of momentum, and the conservation of angular momentum, apply to the isolated systems. Suppose you look at the conservation of energy of the universe as whole.  Now, if you divide up the universe into two parts, say a nitrogen gas tank and the rest of the universe.  The two subsystems will exchange energy and the energies of the individual subsystems will change with time but the energy of the combined system will be unchanging. We will be using arguments of this type throughout this book.
		</p>
		

	</subsection>




	<subsection><title> Examples of Thermodynamic Systems </title>

		<p>
			Following are some examples of thermodynamic systems and ways of specifying their thermodynamic state.
			<ol>
				<li> <alert> Chemically Pure Homogeneous Fluid.</alert> For example, a tank of liquid nitrogen, chemically stable oil in the engine, water in a cooling system of a power plant, etc. The thermodynamic variables here will be pressure (<m>p</m>), temperature (<m>T </m>), density (<m> \rho</m>), volume (<m> V</m>), and mass (<m> M </m>). </li>

				<li> <alert> Chemically Pure Homogeneous Solid.</alert> For example, a train track, a concrete slab, wooden block, etc. The thermodynamic variables here will be pressure (<m>p</m>), temperature (<m>T </m>), density (<m> \rho</m>), volume (<m> V</m>), and mass (<m> M </m>).  </li>

				<li> <alert> Stable Homogeneous Mixture of Several Chemicals.</alert> For example, salty water, chemical reaction products in stationary state, mixture of hydrocarbons, mixture of mixable nonreacting chemicals, etc. The thermodynamic variables here will be pressure (<m>p</m>), temperature (<m>T </m>),  and concentrations (<m> c_i</m>) of each of the chemicals.  </li>

				<li> <alert> Systems with Moving Parts.</alert> For example, a car, which can be thought of consisitng og gasoline, electric circuitry, and moving parts. To specify the state of the car, we will need to specify, not only gasoline, but also the energy in the circuitry and the moving parts. 
				</li>
			</ol>
			The last example clearly shows that everything is a thermodynamic system, and as long as we specify all its relevant observable and changeable macroscopic properties, we would have knowledge of the state of the system. The simplest of all systems is a system that consists of noninteracting particles in a gas state. This is called an <term> ideal gas</term>. The ideal gas is a good model for real gases at low densities when their molecules are far apart.

		</p>
	</subsection>






	<subsection> <title> The Ideal Gas </title>

	</subsection>



</section>