<section xml:id="curved-mirrors"><title> Curved Mirrors </title>
	<introduction>
        <p>
        	You saw in the section above that the image in a plane mirror has the same size as the object and forms at the same distance behind the mirror as the object is located in front of the mirror.  A <term> curved mirror</term>, on the other hand, can form images that may be larger or smaller than the object and may form either in front of the mirror or behind it. Because of the variety of images possible, curved mirrors are exciting optical devices that find many uses.
        </p>
        <p>
        	Since it is much easier to manufacture spherically curved mirrors than other curved shapes, they are more common.  Therefore, here, we will mostly study spherically curved mirrors.  If the reflecting surface is the outer side of the spherical surface the mirror is called a <term> convex mirror</term>, and when the inside surface is the reflecting surface, it is called the <term> concave mirror</term> as illustrated in <xref ref="fig-convex-and-concave-mirror-coatings"/>.    

        </p>
 		<figure xml:id="fig-convex-and-concave-mirror-coatings">
 			<caption>
 				 Reflecting sides of a spherical surface for convex and concave mirrors.
 			</caption>
 			<image source="./images/image-formation/convex-and-concave-mirror-coatings.png" width="70%"/>
 		</figure> 

        <p>
        	Only virtual images form in a convex mirror, while both virtual and real images form in a concave mirror if the object is within half the radius from the vertex. These are illustrated in <xref ref="fig-virtual-images-by-convex-and-concave-mirrors-demo"/>.  In a concave mirror if the object is further away than half the radius from the vertex a real image is formed as illustrated in <xref ref="fig-real-image-from-concave-mirror-demo"/>. No real image is possible from a convex mirror.
        </p>

 		<figure xml:id="fig-virtual-images-by-convex-and-concave-mirrors-demo">
 			<caption>
 				 Virtual images by convex as well as concave mirror.
 			</caption>
 			<image source="./images/image-formation/virtual-images-by-convex-and-concave-mirrors-demo.png" width="70%"/>
 		</figure> 

  		<figure xml:id="fig-real-image-from-concave-mirror-demo">
 			<caption>
 				 Real image by a concave mirror. A convex mirror cannot form a real image.
 			</caption>
 			<image source="./images/image-formation/real-image-from-concave-mirror-demo.png" width="70%"/>
 		</figure>          


    </introduction>

    <subsection><title>Image by Convex Mirror</title>
    	<p>
    		As we saw in the case of image formation by plane mirrors, we can use any two rays from a point object to find the image of that point. In the case of a convex mirror, one can use two of three special rays whis is relatively easy to draw. In order to talk about these special rays, it is helpful to introduce the following notation.
    	</p>
    	<sidebyside widths="50% 5% 45%">
	    	<p>
	    		A convex mirror is made by coating a spherical surface so that reflection occurs at the outside. The center of this sphere is called <term> center</term> (C) of the mirror and the tip of the mirror is called its <term>vertex</term> (V). The point midway between the center and the vertex is the <term>focal point</term> (F) of the mirror. The distance VF is called <term>focal length</term> of the mirror.
	    	</p>
	    	<p></p>
	    	<image source="./images/image-formation/special-points-convex-mirror.png" width="50%"/>
	    </sidebyside>
	    <p>
	    	<xref ref="fig-special-rays-convex-mirror"/> shows three <term>special rays</term> that we will use to draw rays to locate image of an arbitrary object by a convex mirror. 
	    </p>
	 	<figure xml:id="fig-special-rays-convex-mirror">
 			<caption>
 				  Special rays for a convex mirror. (a) Incident ray 1 is directed through the center of the sphere whose surface is coated. The reflected ray <m>1^\prime</m> bounces back along the same line. (b) Incident ray 2 is parallel to the symmetry axis, called the optical axis. The reflected ray <m>2^\prime</m> is in the direction, which if extended behind the mirror, then it will pass through the focal point F. Reverse of this ray is another special ray: <em>if you take a ray that is pointed towards the focal point then, the reflected ray is parallel to the axis</em>. (c) Incident ray 3 is incident at the vertex of the mirror. The reflected ray <m>3^\prime</m> is reflected symmetrically with respect to the axis.
 			</caption>
				<image source="./images/image-formation/special-rays-convex-mirror.png" width="100%"/> 
			</figure> 

    	 	<p><alert> Locating Image of an Arbitrary Point Object By a Convex Mirror: </alert>
    	 	</p>
    	 	<p>
    	 		Now, we will use special rays in a drawing to locate the image of a point object placed in front of a convex mirror. <xref ref="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-convex-mirror-ray-method"/> shows the image formation of a point P by using the special rays 1 and 2 described above.
    	 	</p>
    	 	<sidebyside widths="45% 5% 50%">  
	    	 	<p>
	    	 		When we extrapolate reflected rays <m>1^{\prime}</m> and <m>2^{\prime}</m> they meet at the image point Q.  The image is a virtual image since only the extrapolated rays, not the real rays, meet there.
	    	 	</p>
	    	 	<p></p>
	   	 		<figure xml:id="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-convex-mirror-ray-method">
		 			<caption>
		 				  Using special rays.
		 			</caption>
						<image source="./images/image-formation/locating-image-of-point-object-by-convex-mirror-ray-method.png" width="60%"/> 
	 			</figure>     	 	
	 		</sidebyside>

	 		<sidebyside widths="45% 5% 50%">
	    	 	<p>
	    	 		When you look into this convex mirror it will appear that a likeness of the object P is located at point Q behind the mirror. Here, two additional rays are shown. Since we know the location of image, these additional rays upon reflection appear to come from the image Q.   
	    	 	</p>
	    	 	<p></p>
				<image source="./images/image-formation/locating-image-of-point-object-by-convex-mirror-ray-method-eye.png" width="60%"/>
			</sidebyside> 	    	 	
    	 	<p>
    	 		Unlike the image in a plane mirror, the image behind a convex mirror appears nearer in the mirror than the actual distance of the object from the mirror. That makes convex mirros ideal for situations where you would want to cover a large area such as in the mirrors of a car and the security systems of stores.

    	 	</p> 
    	 	<p>
    	 		Image by a convex mirror is alway behind the mirror. That is, the image is a virtual image, similar to the image by a plane mirror. The orientation is upright in the vertical direction and left-right switched in the horizontal direction.
    	 	</p> 
	    
    	
    	 	
	</subsection>

    <subsection><title>Image by Concave Mirror</title>
	 	<p>
	 		There are three special rays here as well as shown in <xref ref="fig-special-rays-convex-mirror"/>. I have also marked the three special points in the figure - center at C, vertex at V, and focal point F which is located half way between C and V. The distance VF is called <term>focal length</term> of the mirror.
	 	</p>
	 	<figure xml:id="fig-special-rays-concave-mirror">
 			<caption>
 				  Special rays for a concave mirror. (a) Incident ray 1 passes through the center of the sphere whose surface is coated. The reflected ray <m>1^\prime</m> bounces back along the same line. (b) Incident ray 2 is parallel to the symmetry axis, called the optical axis. The reflected ray <m>2^\prime</m> passes through the focal point F. (c) Incident ray 3 is incident at the vertex of the mirror. The reflected ray <m>3^\prime</m> is reflected symmetrically with respect to the axis.
 			</caption>
				<image source="./images/image-formation/special-rays-concave-mirror.png" width="100%"/> 
		</figure>

		<p>
			Image by a concave mirror will behind the mirror if the horizontal distance from V to the object is less than the VF distance. On the otherhand, if the horizontal distance from V to the object is greater than the VF distance, the image will form in front of the mirror. Finally, if if the horizontal distance from V to the object is equal to the VF distance, the image will be at infinity, i.e., you cannot locate the image. We will see these below for a point object. 
		</p>
		<subsubsection><title>Object Within Focal Length of Concave Mirror</title>

			<sidebyside widths="50% 5% 45%">
				<p>
					I will use special rays 1 and 3. <xref ref="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method"/> shows the construction with these rays from the object point P. The reflected rays <m>1^\prime</m> and <m>3^\prime</m> diverge, so they will not cross ever. But, when we extend them back, their extension crosses behind the mirror, where image Q will be located.  
				</p>
				<p></p>
			 	<figure xml:id="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method">
		 			<caption>
		 				  Virtual image of point object within a focal length of a concave mirror.
		 			</caption>
						<image source="./images/image-formation/locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method.png" width="100%"/> 
				</figure>


			</sidebyside>
			<p>
				In <xref ref="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method"/>, we see that vertical distance of the image from the axis is more than that of the object. That will mean, the image of ordinary objects will be enlarged by this mirror if placed in this configuration.
			</p>	
		</subsubsection>


		<subsubsection><title>Object Farther than Focal Length of Concave Mirror</title>

			<sidebyside widths="55% 5% 40%">
				<p>
					Again, I will use special rays 1 and 3. <xref ref="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method-real"/> shows the construction with these rays from the object point P. The reflected rays <m>1^\prime</m> and <m>3^\prime</m> cross at point Q in space which is where image will be located. Since, this is just a space point, you will have to place a screen, such as cardboard, at Q to see the image. This will be a real image. 
				</p>
				<p></p>
			 	<figure xml:id="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method-real">
		 			<caption>
		 				  Real image of point object within a focal length of a concave mirror.
		 			</caption>
						<image source="./images/image-formation/locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method-real.png" width="70%"/> 
				</figure>


			</sidebyside>
			<p>
				In <xref ref="fig-locating-image-of-point-object-by-concave-mirror-ray-method-real"/>, we see that vertical distance of the image from the axis is less than that of the object. That will mean, the image of ordinary objects will be diminished by this mirror if placed in this configuration. The image will also have an upside down orienatation since image point Q is below the axis while object point Q was above the axis.
			</p>	
		</subsubsection>


	</subsection>


	<exercise xml:id="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-Concave-Mirror-Within-a-Focal-Point"><title>Image of a Point on Axis of a Concave Mirror Within a Focal Point</title>

		<statement>
			<p>
				Use a ruler and a protractor to draw rays to find images of point object located on the axis of a concave mirror located at a point within the focal length from the vertex. 
			</p>
		</statement>
		<hint><p>Draw two rays from the point source.</p></hint>
		<answer><p>See the solution.</p></answer>
		<solution>
			<p>
				Drawing two rays from the point source that strike the mirror gives diverging rays <m>1'</m> and <m>2'</m>. When we extend them back, they meet at Q, which is the virtual image of P.
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="fig-exercise-concave-within-focal-ray-diagram">
	 			<caption>
	 				  Ray diagram of <xref ref="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-Concave-Mirror-Within-a-Focal-Point"/>.
	 			</caption>
					<image source="./images/image-formation/exercise-concave-within-focal-ray-diagram.png" width="80%"/> 
			</figure>
			
		</solution>
	</exercise>


	<exercise xml:id="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-Concave-Mirror-Farther-than-a-Focal-Point"><title>Image of a Point on Axis of a Concave Mirror Farther than a Focal Point</title>

		<statement>
			<p>
				Use a ruler and a protractor to draw rays to find images of point object located on the axis of a concave mirror located at a point  farther than the focal length from the vertex.
			</p>
		</statement>
		<hint><p>Draw two rays from the point source.</p></hint>
		<answer><p>See the solution.</p></answer>
		<solution>
			<p>
				Drawing two rays from the point source that strike the mirror givesrays <m>1'</m> and <m>2'</m>, which meet at Q. Therefore, Q is a real image of P.
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="fig-exercise-concave-further-than-focal-ray-diagram">
	 			<caption>
	 				  Ray diagram of <xref ref="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-Concave-Mirror-Farther-than-a-Focal-Point"/>.
	 			</caption>
					<image source="./images/image-formation/exercise-concave-further-than-focal-ray-diagram.png" width="80%"/> 
			</figure>
		</solution>
	</exercise>


	<exercise xml:id="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-ConVex-Mirror-Within-a-Focal-Point"><title>Image of a Point on Axis of a Concave Mirror Within a Focal Point</title>

		<statement>
			<p>
				Use a ruler and a protractor to draw rays to find images of point object located on the axis of a convex mirror located at a point within the focal length from the vertex. 
			</p>
		</statement>
		<hint><p>Draw two rays from the point source.</p></hint>
		<answer><p>See the solution.</p></answer>
		<solution>
			<p>
				Drawing two rays from the point source that strike the mirror gives diverging rays <m>1'</m> and <m>2'</m>. When we extend them back, they meet at Q, which is the virtual image of P.
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="fig-exercise-convex-within-focal-ray-diagram">
	 			<caption>
	 				  Ray diagram of <xref ref="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-ConVex-Mirror-Within-a-Focal-Point"/>.
	 			</caption>
					<image source="./images/image-formation/exercise-convex-within-focal-ray-diagram.png" width="80%"/> 
			</figure>
		</solution>
	</exercise>


	<exercise xml:id="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-Convex-Mirror-Farther-than-a-Focal-Point"><title>Image of a Point on Axis of a Convex Mirror Farther than a Focal Point</title>

		<statement>
			<p>
				Use a ruler and a protractor to draw rays to find images of point object located on the axis of a convex mirror located at a point  farther than the focal length from the vertex.
			</p>
		</statement>
		<hint><p>Draw two rays from the point source.</p></hint>
		<answer><p>See the solution.</p></answer>
		<solution>
			<p>
				Drawing two rays from the point source that strike the mirror gives diverging rays <m>1'</m> and <m>2'</m>. When we extend them back, they meet at Q, which is the virtual image of P.
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="fig-exercise-convex-further-than-focal-ray-diagram">
	 			<caption>
	 				  Ray diagram of <xref ref="exercise-Image-of-a-Point-on-Axis-of-a-Convex-Mirror-Farther-than-a-Focal-Point"/>.
	 			</caption>
					<image source="./images/image-formation/exercise-convex-further-than-focal-ray-diagram.png" width="80%"/> 
			</figure>
		</solution>
	</exercise>










</section>