<section><title> Energy Flow</title>

		<subsection> <title> Work by internal and external forces </title>
			<p>
				We have looked at the conservation of energy from the perspective of conservative and non-conservative forces. The work by conservative forces are included as change in potential energies, which are then combined with change in kinetic energy to give the following equation that says that change in energy is equal to the work by non-conservative forces
				<me>
					 W_{if}^{\text{non-conservative}} = E_f - E_i.
				</me>
			</p>
			<p> Although, when deriving this result no mention was made of whether the system had a single particle or two or more particles. With two or more particles, we make a distinction between internal forces and external forces. Then, this equation can be written more explicitly as
				<men>
					 W_{if}^{\text{nc,ext}} + W_{if}^{\text{nc,int}} = E_f - E_i,
				</men>
				where 'nc' refers to non-conservative, 'ext' to external, and 'int' to internal, and energy <m> E</m> has potential energies from internal and external conservative forces.
				<men>
					E = K_\text{tot} + U_\text{tot}^{\text{int}} +   U_\text{tot}^{\text{ext}}. 
				</men>
			</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection><title> Energy in a conservative system </title>
			<p>
				For concreteness, consider a system that consists of two objects labeled 1 and 2 exerting an <em> attractive conservative force </em> of magnitude <m> F </m> on each other. Since internal force is conservative we call this type of sytem a  a conservative system. Then,  
				<men xml:id="eq-conservation-of-energy-two-objects-calc">
					W_{if}^\text{ext} = (K_f -K_i)_1 + (K_f -K_i)_2 - (W_{on\ 1})_{by\ \vec F} + (W_{on\ 2})_{by\ \vec F}, 
				</men>
					where <m> (W_{on\ 1})_{by\ \vec F}</m> and <m> (W_{on\ 2})_{by\ \vec F} </m> are work done on objects 1 and 2 respectively by the internal forces. Since, we are assuming that this internal force is a conservative force, we can write these works in terms of potentisl enegies.
				<md>
					<mrow> \amp (W_1)_{by\ \vec F} = (U_i^{\text{int}}-U_f^{\text{int}})_1, </mrow>
					<mrow> \amp (W_2)_{by\ \vec F} = (U_i^{\text{int}}-U_f^{\text{int}})_2. </mrow>
				</md>
				Putting these in Eq. <xref ref="eq-conservation-of-energy-two-objects-calc"/> and writing kinetic plus potential as energy <m> E</m> we get
				<me>
					W_{if}^\text{ext} = E_{\text{tot},f} - E_{\text{tot},i},
				</me>
				where
				<me>
					E_{\text{tot}} = E_1 + E_2,
				</me>
				where each <m> E_j </m> is the sum of the kinetic and potential energy of that particle.
			</p>
			<p>
				Therefore, if there are no external forces on a system so that <m> W_{if}^\text{ext}=0</m>, the total energy of a conservative system cannot change.  The energy of the parts of a system, such as that of object 1 or of object 2 in our example, may change with time due to the interaction between them, but the increase in energy of one will be exactly balanced by an equal decrease in energy of the other. 
			</p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection> <title> Principle of conservation of energy </title>
			<p>
				The result arrived for a two-particle system interacting through a conservative force is not limiting at all since all fundamental forces between elementary particles are conservative. Thus, we arrive at a most fundamental law of nature - the <term> principle of conservation of energy</term>.
			</p>
	 
	 		<p>
	 			<em> The energy of an isolated system cannot change with time. </em>
	 		</p>
	 		<p>
		 		We have arrived this law of nature by way of Newton's laws of motion. However, it turns out that this law is even more fundamental than  Newton's laws of motion since energy for isolated systems is conserved even when Newton's laws do not work.
			</p>
			<p>  
				It is interesting to note that for the two bodies in our system, work on 1 by force from 2 and work on 2 by force from 1 are conduits for the transfer of energy from one to the other - this is similar to the role of impulse on 1 by 2 and on 2 by 1 as means by which momentum was transfered between the two bodies.   
			</p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection> <title> Role of heat transfer </title>
			<p>
				 The work by non-conservative forces, whether internally among particles of the same system, or between two systems can be accounted for if the number of particls are small and if the expressions of the forces are known. When we have a large number of particles, it is not possible to perform these calculations in practice.
			</p> 
			<p>
				For macroscopic systems, an alternative approach to energy conservation is taken by introducing new concepts of thermal equilibrium and temperature. A body at higher temperature naturally transfers energy to a body at lower temperature if their contact surface can allow such transfers. You might think of this energy transfer in an analogy to the energy transfer between two particles when they collide - the particle with higher energy tends to give some or all of its energy to the body with lower energy, even in an elastic collision. Such transfers of energy are called heat transfer.
			</p>
			<p>
				The subject of energy transfer due to difference in temperature will be the subject of chapters on thermodynamics.
			</p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection><title> Multiple forms of energy</title>
			<p>
	 			Just as transfer of energy due to a difference in temperature, energy in a system may be stored or released due to chemical changes or chemical reactions. We call these <term> chemical energy</term>, although fundamentally they are just electromagnetic energy. In application of conservation of energy, we take these changes into account as parts of changes in internal potantial energy.
			</p>
			<p>
	 			Similarly, there are also nuclear reactions. The energy involved with these processes are referred to as <term>nuclear energy</term>.
			</p>
			<p>
				In some other processes, radiation may be absorbed or released, carrying energy with them. Radiation may be due to stream of photons or nuclear particles. The energy associated with these processes are called <term>radiation energy</term>.
			</p>
			<p>
				You probably got the idea that energy, which is sum of kinetic and potential energy, of a system may change during the interval from some <m> t_i </m> to some <m> t_f </m>, by many processes which either put energy in the system or take energy away from the system. 
			</p>
			<p>
				At the end of all these processes, an accounting of all energies taken in by the system and all energies lost by the system must give us the following. 
				<men>
					E_f = E_i + \text{(energy flowed IN)} -\text{(energy flowed OUT)}.
				</men>
				This is the bottom line of the principle of conservation of energy.
			</p>

		</subsection>
 

</section>