<section xml:id="energy-Types-of-systems"><title> Types of Systems </title>

	<p> 
		To discuss energy conservation and energy flow, it is helpful to think about whether objects in the system interacts with objects outside the system. With this view in mind, we classify a system in one of the following three categories:
	</p>
	<ol>
		
		<li><alert> Isolated system. </alert> </li> 
		<li> <alert> Closed system. </alert>  </li>
		<li> <alert> Open system. </alert>  </li>
		
	</ol>
	<p>
		An <term> isolated system </term> has no interaction with the external world as if the system was a universe unto itself. No interaction with the external world means
		<me>
			\vec F_{\text{net}}^{\text{ext}} = 0,
		</me>
		which results in no net work and no net impulse by external agents on the objects of the system. Hence, both the total momentum and total energy of an isolated system cannot change. 
	</p>
	<p>
		This type of system is quite uninteresting if you have only one object in the system - all we get is the momentum and energy of the object are fixed in time. An isolated system becomes useful if you have multiple objects in the system which can interact among theselves. Now, the total momentum and total energy remain fixed in time, but momentum and energy of individual parts do change as if total momentum and total energy get redistributed among the parts as time passes.  
	</p>
				
	<p>
		 A <term> closed system</term>, on the other hand, can have interactions with objects outside the system, but the total mass of the objects included in the closed system remains unchanged. For instance, a system consisting of a box sliding down an incline is a closed system: the box is in the system, whose mass is fixed but it interacts with the inclined surface as well with the Earth, which are external to the system.
	</p>

	<p>
		 An <term> open system</term> can have both flow of mass in and out of the system and can interact  with objects outside the system. For instance, a rocket during its launch from Earth is an open system since both its mass is changing and it is interacting with Earth. From above, you might have guessed that most of the time we deal with closed systems.
	</p>
</section>