<section xml:id="section-reflecting-telescope"><title> Reflecting Telescope </title>
	<introduction>
        <p>
        	Isaac Newton designed the first reflecting telescope around 1670 to solve the problem of chromatic aberration that happens in all refracting telescopes. Due to chromatic aberration, the image is blurred with a rainbow of colors around the image.
        </p>
        <p>
        	In the reflecting telescope, light rays from a distant source fall upon the surface of a concave mirror fixed at the bottom end of the tube. The concave mirror focuses the rays on its focal plane. To observe the focused image  Newton used a design in which the focused light from the concave mirror was reflected  to one side of the tube into an eyepiece as shown in <xref ref="fig-telescope-newtonian"/>.  This arrangement is common in many amateur telescopes and is called Newtonian design. 

        </p>

     	<figure xml:id="fig-telescope-newtonian">
    		<caption>
    			    Newtonian design of a reflecting telescope.
    		</caption>
    		<image source="./images/optical-instruments/telescope-newtonian.png" width="100%"/>
    	</figure> 


        <p>

        	Some telescopes reflect the light back towards the middle of the concave mirror by using a convex mirror as shwon in <xref ref="fig-telescope-cassegrain"/>.  In this arrangement the light-gathering concave mirror has a hole in the middle through which light emerges to be incident on the eyepiece lens.  This arrangement of the objective and eyepiece is called <term>Cassegrainian design</term>.\   Most big telescopes, including Hubble telescope (see <xref ref="fig-telescope-hubble"/>),  are of this design.  There are other arrangements also possible. Sometimes one puts a light detector right at the spot where light is focused by the curved mirror.
        </p> 

      	<figure xml:id="fig-telescope-cassegrain">
    		<caption>
    			Cassegrainian design of a reflecting telescope.
    		</caption>
    		<image source="./images/optical-instruments/telescope-cassegrain.png" width="100%"/>
    	</figure> 
      
 

		<p>
			Most of the research telescopes are now of reflecting type.  One of the largest telescopes of this kind is the Hale 200-inch or 5-meter built on Mount Palomar in southern California. The measurement of 200 inches here refers to the diameter of the mirror.  In 2012, the largest telescope was the 10 meter Keck telescope at the Keck observatory on the summit of the dormant Mauna Kea volcano, in Hawaii.  At the Keck observatory there are two 10 meter telescopes. They are not single mirror, but instead  made up of 36 hexagonal mirrors each.  Furthermore, the two telescopes on the Keck can work together through an interference which increases their power to an effective 85-meter mirror! 
		</p>
		<p> 
			Hubble telescope shown in <xref ref="fig-telescope-hubble"/>, put in the orbit around earth in 1990, is another large reflecting telescope with the primary mirror of diameter 2.4 meter. That makes <m>f_\text{o}= 2.4/4 = 0.6\text{m}</m>.
		</p>

      	<figure xml:id="fig-telescope-hubble">
    		<caption>
    			Hubble Space Telescope as seen from the Space Shuttle Discovery on mission STS-82. (NASA, Feb 1997, see http://hubble.nasa.gov)
    		</caption>
    		<image source="./images/optical-instruments/telescope-hubble.png" width="100%"/>
    	</figure> 


		<p>
			The formula for the angular magnification <m>M</m> of  a reflecting telescope is same as that of the refracting telescope.
			<men>
				M_\text{telesccope} = - \frac{f_\text{o}}{f_\text{e}} = - \frac{R_\text{o}}{2f_\text{e}},
			</men>
			where <m>f_\text{o}</m> is half of the radius of curvature, <m>R_\text{o}</m>,  of the objective mirror and <m>f_\text{e}</m> is the focal length of the eyepiece.  You can see that making large objective not only helps out with collecting more light into the telescope it also helps with the  magnification of the image.
        </p>
    </introduction>
</section>