<section xml:id="sec-Energy-Source-of-Sun"><title>Energy Source of Sun</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			The energy for most main-sequence stars come from nuclear fusion of protons into helium. For instance, it is believed that the chain of fusion reactions shown in <xref ref="fig-astro-p-p-1-chain"/>, called the <term>proton-proton chain - I</term>, occur in the Sun.
		</p>

		<figure xml:id="fig-astro-p-p-1-chain">
			<caption>
				 
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/modern-physics/astro-p-p-1-chain.png" width="90%"/>
		</figure>
 
			<!-- <mdn>
				<mrow>\amp  \textrm{p} + \textrm{p}  \longrightarrow\ ^{2}H + e^{+} + \nu_e</mrow>
				<mrow> \amp ^{2}\textrm{H} + \textrm{p} \longrightarrow\ ^{3}\textrm{He} + \gamma </mrow>
				<mrow> \amp ^{3}\textrm{He} + ^{3}\textrm{He} \longrightarrow\ ^{4}\textrm{He} +   \textrm{p} +  \textrm{p} </mrow>
			</mdn> -->
 		<p>
			In the first reaction, two protons are fused to make a deuteron, a positron, and a neutrino. 
			In the second reaction, the deuteron fuses with another proton with the production of <m>^{3}\textrm{He}</m>.  Two <m>^{3}\textrm{He}</m> then combine to form <m>^{4}\textrm{He}</m> and release two protons. Thus, two times the first two reactions and one time the third equation forms a full cycle.  In the full chain, four protons combine in the first reaction and two in the second reaction, and two protons are released in the third reaction.  Thus, a total of four protons combine to yield  one <m>^{4}\textrm{He}</m>, two positrons, two neutrino, and two photons.
		</p>
		<p>
			The net energy released as positron, neutrino, and gamma rays over one proton-proton chain will be
			\[
			Q_{\textrm{net}} = \left(4 m_p -  m[\ ^{4}\textrm{He}]   \right)\: c^2\approx 25\:\textrm{MeV}.
			\]	
			When the two positrons collide with two electrons in the Sun, they annihilate each other and produce gamma rays with additional energy of approximately 2 MeV. This makes the total energy released from the proton-proton chain plus annihialtion of positron to be about 27 MeV per four proton. The proton-proton chain reaction occurs deep inside the Sun where the temperature is quite high,   <m>\sim 15</m> MK.

		</p>
	</introduction>
</section>