<section xml:id="Energy-in-Capacitors"><title> Energy in Capacitors  </title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			A capacitor is an energy-storing device. By storing charges separated by a distance, the capacitor essentially stores energy in the potential energy of the charges, or equivalently in the electric field of the space between plates. 
		</p>
		<p>
			One way to easily figure out the energy stored in a capacitor is to use energy conservation in the discharging circuit. Connect a charged capacitor to a resistor <m>R</m> and let current flow in the simple RC-circuit and determine the net energy dissipated in the resistor.  When current <m>I(t)</m> passes through a resistor, the instantaneous power-dissipation rate, <m>P(t) = I(t)^2 R</m>, as we have seen before.  
		</p>
		<p>
			We have already found the following expression for current at instant <m>t</m> in discharging circuit in which the initial charg eon the capacitor is <m>Q_0</m>.
			<me>
				I(t) = \dfrac{Q_0}{RC}\, \exp{\left( -t/RC\right ) }.
			</me>
			Therefore, instantaneous power dissipated in the resistor will be
			<men xml:id="eq-instantaneous-power-in-discharging-capacitor">
				P(t) = \dfrac{Q_0^2}{RC^2}\, \exp{\left( -2t/RC\right ) }.
			</men>
		</p>
		<p>
			This equation tells us the rate at which energy is being discharged by the capacitor. Therefore, energy discharged between <m>t</m> and <m>t+\Delta t</m> will be
			<me>
				\Delta U = P(t)\Delta t.
			</me>
			Therefore, integrating Eq. <xref ref="eq-instantaneous-power-in-discharging-capacitor"/> from <m>t=0</m> to <m>t=T</m> will give us the amount of energy discharged during this time.
			<men>
				U = \int_0^T P(t)\; dt.
			</men>
			You can show that this leads to
			<men>
				U = U_0\left( 1 - e^{-2T/RC}\right),
			</men>
			where <m>U_0</m> is the energy in the capacitor at time <m>t=0</m>, as we will interpret below.
			<me>
				U_0 = \frac{1}{2}Q_0 V_0.
			</me>
		</p>
		<p>
			By taking <m>T=\infty</m> we get all energy that was dissipated in the resistor.
			<me>
				E_\text{dissipated} = \dfrac{1}{2}\dfrac{Q_0^2}{C}.
			</me>
			But, by conservation of energy in the circuit, this energy must have been originally stored in the capacitor. Therefore, a capacitor of capacitance <m>C</m> charged to <m>Q_0</m> stores the following energy. Since this energy is potential energy, we use symbol <m>U</m> for it.
			<me>
				U_\text{in capacitor} = \dfrac{1}{2}\dfrac{Q_0^2}{C}.
			</me>
			By using the capacitor formula, <m>Q=CV</m>, we can write this in other forms.
			<men>
				U_\text{in capacitor} = \dfrac{1}{2}\dfrac{Q_0^2}{C} = \dfrac{1}{2}Q_0V_0 = \dfrac{1}{2}CV_0^2.
			</men>

		</p>
	</introduction>

	<exercise xml:id="ex-Energy-from-Discharging-a-Capacitor"><title>Energy from Discharging a Capacitor </title>

		<statement>
			<p>
				(a) A capacitor of capacitance <m>2.0\text{ mF}</m> is charged by a <m>1.5\text{-V}</m> battery. How much total energy will be released when this capacitor is discharged?
			</p>
			<p>
				(b) If discharging circuit has resistance <m>5.0\;\Omega</m>, how much time will it take to get <m>70\%</m> of the energy?
			</p>
		</statement>
		<hint><p>
			(a) Use total energy formula. (b) Use finite time formula.
		</p></hint>
		<answer><p>
			(a) <m>2.25\text{ mJ}</m>, (b) <m>1.78\text{ ms}</m>.
		</p></answer>
		<solution><title>(a)</title>
			<p>
				(a)
				The energy released will be equal to the energy stored in the capacitor. Since <m>C</m> and <m>V_0</m> are given, we use the formula using these.
				<me>
					U_0 = \frac{1}{2}CV_0^2 = \frac{1}{2}\times 2.0\text{ mF}\times  (1.5\text{ V})^2 =  2.25\text{ mJ}.
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
		<solution><title>(b)</title>
			<p>
				(b)
				Energy released in time <m>t=0</m> to <m>t=T</m> is
				<me>
					U = U_0 \left( 1 - e^{-2t/RC}\right).
				</me>
				We are given the following.
				<me>
					\frac{U}{U_0} = 0.3,\ \ RC = 5\times 2\times 10^{-3} = 0.01\text{ s}.
				</me>
				Therefore, we have the following equation to solve.
				<me>
					0.3 = 1 - e^{-200\,t}.
				</me>
				We first isolate the exponential on one side and take natural log to solve this.
				<me>
					t = -\frac{ \ln\;0.7 }{200} = 1.78\text{ ms}.
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</exercise>











</section>