<section xml:id="Electric-Field-Lines"><title>  Electric Field Lines </title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			When we join electric fields at various points, we get a diagram of directed lines, which are called <term>electric field lines</term>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			The electric field lines of a single positive charge are <em> straight lines in all directions from the charge</em> and the electric field of a single negative charge are <em> straight lines in all directions landing on the charge</em>. See <xref ref="electri-field-lines-of-a-single-charge"/>.
		</p>
		<p>
			The electric field lines of two or more charges can be constructed from the net electric field  of each of the charges. In the exercises in <xref ref="Superposition-of-Electric-Fields" />, you have shown that direction of electric field of a two charge system varies in space. Therefore, we construct elctric field lines such that <em>the electric field at a point on the line will be tangent to the line</em>. <xref ref="fig-e-field-two-opposite-charges"/> shows electric field for two equal charges of opposite types and <xref ref="fig-e-field-two-positive-charges"/> shows electric field for two positive charges. What do you think the electric field lines of two negative charges will look like?
		</p>
		<figure xml:id="fig-e-field-two-opposite-charges">
 			<image source="./images/coulombs-law/E-field-two-particle-1.png" width="80%"/>
			<caption>
				Electric field lines for two oppositely charged particles of equal amount. Ref: <url source="https://www.wolframcloud.com/objects/demonstrations/ElectricFieldsForThreePointCharges-source.nb"> Wolfram Demonstrations</url>.
			</caption>
		</figure>

		<figure xml:id="fig-e-field-two-positive-charges">
 			<image source="./images/coulombs-law/E-field-two-particle-2.png" width="80%"/>
			<caption>
				Electric field lines for two positive charges of equal amount.  Ref: <url source="https://www.wolframcloud.com/objects/demonstrations/ElectricFieldsForThreePointCharges-source.nb"> Wolfram Demonstrations</url>.
			</caption>
		</figure>

	</introduction>

	<subsection> <title>Graphical Definition of Electric Field </title>
		<p>
			Using the idea of electric field lines it is possible to introduce a qualitative and more pictorial definition of electric field. According to this approach, we envision space filled with electric field lines from charges according to the following rules.
		</p>
		<ol>
			<li>The tangent to an electric field line at a point gives the direction of the electric field at that point. </li>
			<li> The number of field lines per unit are passing through an imaginary surface normal to the lines corresponds to the magnitude of the electric field.</li>
		</ol>
		<p>
			This graphical definition of electric field is  useful in visualizing electric field.
		</p>
	</subsection>



</section>