<section><title> Common Forces</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			There are four fundamental forces in nature - gravitational, elctromagnetic, weak-nuclear, and strong-nuclear forces. But, in everyday life, we encounter many effective forces that have their origins in gravitational and elctromagnetic forces. We will mostly study the following forces in this chapter. After this list of forces, each is described in some detail. You can come back to them as you need them.
		</p>
		<p>
			<ol>
				<li> Weight </li>
				<li> Normal </li>
				<li> Static Friction </li>
				<li> Sliding/Kinetic Friction </li>
				<li> Rolling Friction </li>
				<li> Fluid Drag </li>
				<li> Spring Force </li>
				<li> Tension Force</li>
			</ol>
		</p>

		<p>
			We will be working in the SI system of units, in which the unit for force is Newton, abbreviated by capital letter <m> \text{N}</m>. How big a <m> 1 \text{ N}</m> force? Using the second law of Newton, we can say that <m> 1 \text{ N}</m> force on a <m> 1 \text{ kg}</m> object will cause the object to accelerate at <m> 1\text{ m/s}^2</m>.
		</p>
	</introduction>
	<subsection> <title> Weight </title>
		<p>
			The weight is the name of the force between Earth and the body under study. When the force of weight acts on an object, we simply call it the weight of the object.  When the force of weight acts on Earth, it does not make much difference since the main force on Earth is by the Sun, which is a very large force.
		</p>
		<p>
			We will denote the weight force on the body by the symbol <m> \vec W</m>. 
			<me>
				\vec W_\text{on object}^\text{by Earth} \text{ denoted by } \vec W.
			</me>
			Sometimes, we will place a subscript letter to denote the weight on a particular body if there are more than one body of interest in a situation. The magnitude will be the same symbol without the arrow over, <m> W </m>.
		</p>

		<p>
			The magnitude of weight of an object near Earth, is very nearly independent of the object's distance from Earth. If the mass of the object is <m> m </m>, then magnitude of weight is
			<men xml:id="eq-weight-magnitude">
				\text{Magnitude of weight, } W= m\, g, \ \ \ \text{ near Earth's surface,}
			</men>
			where <m> g </m> is called acceleration due to gravity, which has a standard value <m> 9.81 \text{ m/s}^2</m>.  		
		</p>
		<sidebyside widths="50% 50%">

			<p>
				The weight acting on the object has a direction pointed vertically down and perpendicular to the locally flat surface of the Earth. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<image source="./images/forces/weight-vector.png" width="50%" />
			</p>			
		</sidebyside>
		<p> 
			Note that although weight is intimately connected to mass, <alert>weight is not mass</alert>. Weight is a force, which is a vector, while mass is a simple positive scalar quantity. We might <alert> define mass </alert> by this relation, i.e., we might say, mass is a physical property of an object that has the value equal to its weight divided by a standard number <m> g </m>. A spring scale uses this definition of mass. But, this is not the fundamental definition of mass in physics. The defnition of mass in physics is based on Newton's second law of motion, which we will discuss later in this chapter.
		</p>
		<p>
			The force of weight on a a particle-like object acts just on the particle. But most regularly encountered object, such as car, are made of many particles or parts. Then, it can be shown that the influence of weight on the motion of such an object is same as if the weight acted on a special point in space, called the <term> center of gravity </term> of the object. 
		</p>
		<sidebyside widths="60% 40%">
			<p>
				The figure shows a crescent-shaped object, whose center of gravity is at a point outside the body. The sum of the weights acting on all parts of this body turns out be equal to the weight of a particle of same mass a the mass of the object placed at the center of gravity point.
			</p>
			<p>
				<image source="./images/forces/weight-vector-at-cg.png" width="70%" />
			</p>

		</sidebyside>

		<exercise><title> Weight of a Dumb-bell-Shaped Object </title>
			<statement>
				<sidebyside widths="60% 20%">
					<p> The object shown in the figure has two large masses, each of <m> 200\text{ kg}</m>, with a relatively light bent bar, whose mass may be ignored. 
					</p>
					<image source="./images/forces/cp-weight-acts-on-center.png"/>
				</sidebyside>
				<p> (a) What is the weight of the dumb-bell?

				</p>
				<p> (b) What des the weight of the dumb-bell act? Show by drawing an arrow with tail at the point you think it acts.
					
				</p>
			</statement>
			<hint> <p>  Use definition </p> </hint>
			<answer> <p>  (a) <m> 3924\text{ N} </m>, (b) See solution. </p> </answer>
			<solution> 
				<p>(a)
					<me>
						mg = 2\times 200\times 9.81 = 3924\text{ kg.m/s}^2 = 3924\text{ N}.
					</me>
				</p>
				<p> (b)
					<image source="./images/forces/cp-weight-acts-on-center-b.png" widht="25%"/>
				</p>
			</solution>
		</exercise>



	</subsection>

	<subsection><title> Normal Force </title>

		<p>
			When two solid bodies are pushed into each other, they develop a repulsive force at the surface (or point) of contact. Why does that happen? Think of molecules of each solid body as springs, which become compressed when pushed in from outside. As a result, they push out and away from the body. We call this <term> reactive force </term> the normal force.
		</p>
		<p>
			We will denote the normal force by either symbol <m>\vec F_N</m> or <m> \vec N </m>, and the magnitude by the same symbol without an arrow over the symbol.
		</p>
		<p>
			Unlike the force of weight, there is <alert> no formula for the magnitude of the normal force</alert>. If you have memorized some formula for the magnitude of the normal force, such as <m> F_N = mg </m> and <m> F_N = mg\cos\,\theta</m>, then you need to forget that incorrect knowledge. <alert> You cannot get the magnitude of the normal force without applying Newton's second law of motion.</alert> That is why, we will not practice it here.
		</p>
		<p>
			As far as the direction is concerned, we have the <alert> guidance that the force is repulsive</alert>. Therefore, for a normal force between two bodies A and B, when the normal force acts on A, it is pointed away from B, and when it acts on B, it is pointed away from A. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert>The normal force is perpendicular to the surface of contact</alert>. It is easy to get the normal direction if the surface of contact is planar. If the surface of contact is curved, the direction of normal force will vary over the surface of contact, being normal to the local tangent plane of the surface.
		</p>

		<sidebyside widths="50% 50%">
			<p>
				<alert>  Normal force across the surface of contact may not have the same value </alert>- it will be greater where the bodies are more pressed and less where less pressed. 
				The box on the wedge presses more at points that are at lower points since the weight of more parts of the box acts there. This results in more normal force in lower parts than upper parts. That means the net normal force does not go through the center of the box, but a little bit right of the center in this figure.
			</p>
			<p>
				<image source="./images/forces/normal-force.png" width="70%" />
			</p>
		</sidebyside>

		<p> 
			Therefore, when we draw a single arrow to represent normal force on a body, we let the arrow pass through the center of the surface of the contact if normal force is uniform across the surface, otherwise we draw the arrow more near where the normal force is expected to be larger.
		</p>
 

	</subsection>

	<subsection><title> Static Friction </title>
		<subsubsection><title> Static Friction Force</title>
			<p>
				Two solid bodies in contact may stick together to some extent due to inter-molecular forces between the two bodies. <em> If you attempt to slide one body over the other,</em> these bonds stretch out a little, which creates an attractive force between the two bodies. We call this <alert> reactive force </alert> the force of static friction. <em> Note that, without the applied force that is attempting to slide the two bodies over each other, there is no static friction between them.</em>
			</p>
			<p>
				We will denote the static friction force by the symbol <m> \vec F_s</m> and the magnitude by the same symbol with an arrow.
			</p>
			<p>
				Just as the normal force, there is no formula for the magnitude of static friciton force. Here, if you have memorized any formula for <m> \vec F_s</m> or  <m> F_s</m>, it would be better to forget them. For instance, a common wrong formula often memorized is <m> F_s = \mu_s F_N </m>. This formula is only correct when <m> F_s </m> takes the maximum value as discussed below; this formula is used to define the static friction coefficient <m> \mu_s</m> and not to give you a formula for <m> F_s </m>.
			</p>
			<p>
				The direction of the static friction force is obtained by the attractive nature of the force and that the force is pointed in the plane of the contact surface if the contact is planar or in the tangent plane if the surface of contact is curved.  
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="fig-static-friction">
				<caption>
					Static fricion force opposes the applied force. When acting on the body on which the applied force is acting, it is in the opposite direction to the applied force. But when acting on the other object, here the table, the static friction force is in the same direction as the applied force.
				</caption>
				<image source="./images/forces/static-friction.png" width="70%"/>
			</figure>
			<p>
				Just like the normal force, static friction force may vary across the surface of contact. When making a diagram in which we draw one arrow for the static friction force, we will draw the arrow near locations where we expect the largest value.
			</p>
		</subsubsection>
		<subsubsection><title> Maximum Static Friction Force</title>
			<p>
				In the example of book on the table, as you push the book gently, say with increasing force. You find that, your force is balanced by the static friction force up to a limit, but, if the applied force is above that limit, the book starts to slide on the table. 
			</p>

			<p>
				These observations mean that, under a given condition, there can be only so much static friction before the bodies start to slide.
				We denote the magnitude of this <term> maximum static friction </term> by <m> F_s^{\text{max}} </m>. The value of <m> F_s^{\text{max}} </m> can be found experimentally. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The ratio of <m> F_s^{\text{max}} </m> to the magnitude of the normal force <m> F_N </m> for a surface turns out to be a characteristic of the surface of contact. We call this ratio the coefficient of static friction.
				<men>
					\mu_s = \dfrac{F_s^{\text{max}}}{F_N}.
				</men>
				If two surfaces are stuck together, then they cannot slide past each other. In that case <m>\mu_s = \infty </m>, and if you don't need any force to slide, i.e., for a frictionless surface, <m>\mu_s = 0 </m>. That is, <m> 0 \le \mu_s \lt \infty</m>.
			</p>
		</subsubsection>
	</subsection>
	<subsection> <title> Sliding/Kinetic Friction </title> 
		<p>
			We found above that static friction prevents slide across the surface of contact up to a limit. If you need more static friction that the maximum static friction <m> F_s^{\text{max}}</m> available under the condition, then the two body in contact will move relative to each other. This movement is called <term> sliding</term>.
		</p>
		<p>
			Once again, let a book be placed on a table, and let us push the book with a horizontal force. The pushing causes the reactive force of static friction to develop between the book and the table at the surface of their contact. But, if the applied force is so great that the static friction that would have to develop would exceed the maximum static friction possible, then the book will slide on the table. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert> When the book is sliding,</alert> the surface(s) of contact between the book and table still provides an attractive force along the contact surface, resulting in a friction force called the sliding or <term>kinetic friction force</term>. I prefer the term <term>sliding friction</term>, but most books use the term kinetic friction. 
		</p>
		<p>
			We will denote the kinetic friction force by the symbol, <m> \vec F_k </m> and the magnitude by the same symbol without the arrow. 
		</p>
		<p>
			Just as the normal force, there is no formula for the magnitude of kinetic friciton force. The direction of the kinetic friction force on a body is in the opposite direction of the slide. For instance, if book on the table is sliding towards East, the kinetic friction <m> \vec F_k </m> on the book will be pointed towards West, and the kinetic friction <m> \vec F_k </m> on the table will be pointed towards East.
		</p>
		<p>
			Although, there is no notion of maximum kinetic friction, the ratio of the magnitude of the kinetic friction <m> F_k </m> and the normal force for the surface is a  characteristic of that surface. We call this ratio the coeffient of kinetic friction and denote it by <m> \mu_k</m>.
			<men>
				\mu_k = \dfrac{F_k}{F_N}.
			</men>
		</p>

	</subsection>

	<subsection><title> Rolling Friction </title>

		<p>
			Friction of rolling bodies is a little different than the static and kinetic frictions we discussed above. Suppose you roll a wheel on a foam. You will notice that the wheel deforms the foam at the surface of contact. The same type of momentary deformation happens between the wheel of the car and the road. If the wheel is not to slide, there cannot be any relative motion of the road and the wheel - that is, the small surface of contact has a static friction when you roll the wheel. This static friction is called the rolling friction.
		</p>
		<p>
			Since the surface of contact is small during the rolling process, the maximum rolling friction is usually considerably smaller than the maximum static friction for the same type of surfaces in contact.
		</p>
		<p> 
			We will denote the rolling friction force by <m> \vec F_r </m> and the magnitude by the same symbol without the arrow. Since, rolling friction is a static friction, we have a limiting value, which will be denoted by <m> F_r^{\text{max}}</m>. A coefficient of rolling friction, <m> \mu_r </m>, can be defined similarly to static and kinetic friction coefficients.
			<men>
				\mu_r = \dfrac{F_r^{\text{max}}}{F_N}.
			</men>
		</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection><title> Drag Force </title>

		<p>
			The drag force is the force that the fluid applies on a moving body in the fluid. This type of friction is different from kinetic friction between solids - while the kinetic friction did not depend on the speed of the object, the drag force depends on the speed.

		</p>
		<p> 
			The direction of the drag force is, just like the kinetic friction, in the opposite direction of the velocity of the moving object.
		</p>
		<sidebyside widths="55% 40%">
			<p>
				The magnitude of the drag force  is proportional to one power of speed if the body is moving slowly so that a laminar flow of fluid around the object occurs as shown in the figure. In this range of speed, 
				the drag is dominated by viscous effects of the fluid. This type of drag is called <term> Stoke's force</term>, <term> linear drag force</term> or <term> viscous drag force</term>.
				<men>
					F_{D}^{\text{viscous}} = b\, v,
				</men>
				where the coefficient <m> b </m> depends on geometric fearturs of the object and viscosity of the fluid. For instance, for a spherical ball of radius <m> R </m> moving through a fluid of viscosity <m> \eta </m>, the linear drag force has the following expression.
				<men>
					b = 6\pi\eta R.
				</men>
			</p>
			<image source="./images/forces/linear-drag-stokes.png"/>

		</sidebyside>

		<p>
			If the body is moving rapidly, the flow of the fluid around the object is no longer laminar. The resistive force of the fluid is mainly as a reaction to the impulse on the fluid by the moving ball. Suppose a spherical ball is moving through a fluid at speed <m> v </m> - this would mean that from the perspective of the ball, the fluid in front of the ball would be striking the ball at speed <m> v </m> and depositing their momentum on the ball. Every second the fluid will deposit a momentum equal to
			<me>
				\Delta p = \text{Volume}\times \text{Density} \times v,
			</me>
			where Volume is the volume in front of the ball of a cylinder of cross-section equal to the cross-section of the ball, i.e., here <m> \pi R^2</m>, and the height equal to <m> v</m>, since in one second, all the fluid up to this distance would have hit the ball. Writing <m> \rho </m> for the density of the fluid, we get the rate at which momentum is deposited by the fluid on the ball in the opposite direction to the fluid flow is
			<me>
				\dfrac{\Delta p}{\Delta t} =  \pi R^2 \rho v^2. 
			</me>
			We usually write a more general formula that can apply to other shapes.
			<me>
				\dfrac{\Delta p}{\Delta t} = \dfrac{1}{2}\,C_D\, A\, \rho\, v^2, 
			</me>
			where <m> A </m> is the frontal area of cross-section of the moving object that is blocking the fluid flow past the body, and <m> C_D </m> the <term> drag coefficient </term>. 
			The rate of change of momentum acts as a resistive force. It is called the <term> inertial drag force</term>.
			<men>
				F_{D}^{\text{inertial}} = \dfrac{1}{2}\,C_D\, A\, \rho\, v^2. 
			</men>			
		</p>
		<p>
			The drag coefficient <m> C_D</m> is a dimensionless number that depends on shape and speed in a complicated way. You can set <m> C_D \approx 1 </m> in most situations to get a sense of the amount of drag, but for more exact value, you would need to find <m> C_D</m> experimentally. For problems, either this number is usually provided with the statement of the problem or the number can be looked up in a table.
		</p>

		<p>

			<table ><title ></title >
				<caption> Representative <m> C_D </m> Values. The values in the table are from wikipedia sources. A good resource: https://www.engineeringtoolbox.com/drag-coefficient-d_627.html
				</caption>
				<tabular halign ="left" >
					<row bottom ="major" >
						<cell > Object </cell >
						<cell > <m>C_D </m > </cell >
					</row >
					<row bottom ="minor">
						<cell >Smooth sphere ( <m> Re=10^{5}  </m>) </cell >
						<cell ><m> 0.47 </m> </cell >
						
					</row >
					<row bottom ="minor">
						<cell > Car</cell >
						<cell ><m> 0.25	</m> </cell >
					</row >
					<row bottom ="minor">
						<cell > Skier </cell >
						<cell > <m> 1.0 - 1.1 </m> </cell >
					</row >
					<row bottom ="major">
						<cell > Boeing 787 </cell >
						<cell >0.024 </cell >
					</row >
					<row bottom ="major">
						<cell > Dophin </cell >
						<cell >0.0036 </cell >
					</row >


				</tabular >
			</table >

		</p>


		<p> 
			<alert> Shoud I use <m>F_{D}^{\text{viscous}}</m> or <m> F_{D}^{\text{inertial}} </m>? </alert> Since both drags are present all the time, we need to see if we need to use both or if one of them is extremely dominant. A ratio of the inertial drag to viscous drag could be used to test how big one is compared to the other. For tha ball, we get
			<me>
				\dfrac{F_D^{\text{inertial}}}{F_D^{\text{viscous}}} = \dfrac{C_D}{12} \dfrac{\rho R v}{\eta}.
			</me>
			Rather than this formukla,  we actually use a related dimensionless quantity, called the Reynold's number, defined by
			<me>
				N_R = \dfrac{2R\, \rho\,  v}{\eta},
			</me> 
			In general, we replace <m> 2R </m> by a suitable measure of a length scale <m> L </m>  of the moving object that is being pushed against by the fluid flow.

			<men>
				N_R = \dfrac{L\, \rho\,  v}{\eta},
			</men> 

 			The rule of thumb is that if <m> N_R \gt\gt 1 </m>, use  the inertial drag, and, if <m> N_R \lt\lt 1 </m> use the simpler linear drag, otherwise use the sum of the two. 
 
		</p>
		<p>
			The drag force we have discussed in this section is a very simplified picture of what actually goes on when fluid is flowin past an object. These simplified/over-simplified picture non-the-less give us a rough idea of the physics involved.
		</p>


	</subsection>

	<subsection><title> Spring Force</title>
		<p> 
			Springs can be stretched or compressed changing their original length. When a spring is stretched, it pulls in the two bodies on the two ends, providing an attractive force between the two bodies. When a spring is compressed, it pushes away the two bodies on the two ends, providing a repulsive force between the two bodies. 
		</p>
		<sidebyside widths="55% 45%">
			<p>
				The forces generated on the two ends of the spring due to the change in the length of the spring are called spring forces on the two bodies. We denote the magnitude of these spring forces by a common symbol <m> F_{\text{sp}}</m>. Let <m> \Delta l </m> be the absolute value of the change in length, positive for both amount of stretch and amount of compression. Then, <m> F_{\text{sp}}</m> is given by
				<men> 
					F_{\text{sp}} = k\, \Delta l,
				</men>
				where <m> k </m> is called <term> spring constant</term>. A stiffer spring has larger value of <m> k </m>.
			</p>
			<image source="./images/forces/spring-force.png" width="70%"/>
		</sidebyside>
		<p>
			Often, one end of the spring is fixed to a fixed support. In the figure above, let B be a fixed support, then, the change in the length of the spring is completely dependent on the position of the block A on the other end.
		</p>
		
		<sidebyside widths="55% 45%">
			<p> 
				We will then place positive <m> x </m> axis in the direction of A and place the origin at the point where A is present when the spring is neither stretched nor compressed. Let <m> x </m> be the <m> x </m> coordinate of the block A at some instant <m> t </m>. Then 
					<me>
						\Delta l = |x|.
					</me>
			</p>
			<image source="./images/forces/spring-force-x-axis.png" width="70%"/>
		</sidebyside>
		<p>
			Then, the spring force vector on A can be written more simply in terms of the unit vector <m> \hat i</m> for the <m> x </m> axis. 
			<men>
				\vec F_{\text{sp}}^{\text{on A}} = - k\, x\, \hat i.
			</men>
			We don't always have to be so verbose and write <q>on A</q> all the time. The object on which the force is acting in a particular situation may be clear from the context.
		</p>

	</subsection>

	<subsection><title> Tension Force</title>
		<p>
			Many common situations involve tying two objects by using a rope or a string. When the connecting string is taut, the string acts as a stretched spring and pulls in the the two bodies at the two ends. We say that the taut string provided at tension force on the two bodies. 
		</p>

		<sidebyside widths="55% 35%">
			<p>
				We will denote the magnitude of the tension force by <m> F_T</m>. Say, two objects A and B are connected by a taut string, then we will say that the string has a tension <m> F_T </m>. When this tension force acts on A, we have the tension force vector <m> \vec F_{T}^{\text{on A}}</m>, and when it acts on B, we have the tension force vector <m> \vec F_{T}^{\text{on A}}</m>. Even though these two forces are different forces, we will often use the same symbol for them and which one we mean will be clear from the context.
			</p>
			<image source="./images/forces/tension-force.png" width="70%"/>	
		</sidebyside>
		<p>
			Unlike the spring force, we do not have any formula for the magnitude of the tension force. If you have memorized formulas such as <m> F_T = mg</m>, then you need to forget that since there is no such law. The magnitude of tension is obtained by requiring the consistency of Newton's laws of motion applied to everything that is affected by the string.
		</p>

		
		<sidebyside widths="55% 35%">	
			<p>
				For instance, in Atwood machine, two blocks are tied together by a string and then hung over a pulley. If the masses of the blocks are different, then pulley will rotate. Assuming the string is not sliding on the pully surface, the motions of the masses and pulley are connected. This requires static friction force between the string and the pulley surface, which has the effect of string becoming essentially two strings, one on the left and the other on the right. The two sides of the string, then, have two different magnitudes, <m> T_1 </m> and <m> T_2 \ne T_1</m>.
			</p>
			<image source="./images/forces/tension-force-atwood-machine.png" width="70%"/>
		</sidebyside>
		<p>
			If pulley was massless or if string slid without friction on the pulley surface, the two sides of the string remain as one string. In these situations, the tensions on the two sides of the pulley have the same magnitude <m> T_1 = T_2 </m>; in this case, we use same symbol, <m> T</m>, for the tensions on the two sides, regardless of the masses of the two blocks.  
		</p>

	</subsection>







</section>