<section xml:id="forces-Newtons-First-and-Second-Laws-of-Motion"><title> Newton's First and Second Laws of Motion </title>


	<subsection> <title> Newton's First Law of Motion </title>
		<p>
			This law is also called the <term>law of inertia</term>. It states that, 
			you do not need any force for maintaining a constant velocity motion!! 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert> This is contrary to our everyday experience.</alert>  We find that objects normally tend to slow down and come to a stop unless someone continuously pushes on them. Galileo demonstrated that slowing down is usually caused by ubiquitous friction force, and, if you were to find an ideal frictionless environment, the steady constant velocity motion will be perpetual.
		</p>
		<p>
			You may be wondering: <q> Why can't the velocity of an object go to zero without a force? What propels objects  at constant velocity to be in their perpetual motion?</q> There is really no answer to these questions. Instead, we assert that nature has an inherent tendency of maintaining the motion. We give this natural tendency a name - the <term> inertia </term> of motion. But beware that giving a name is not the same thing as having an explanation!
		</p>

	</subsection>


	<subsection> <title>Newton's Second Law of Motion  </title>
		<p>
			Consider an object of fixed mass, say a block of steel. When you apply a force on it, you find that its speed and/or direction of motion changes. This is what happens, for instance, when you let it fall or if you spin it in a circle. This is a universal behavior. 
		</p>
		<p>
			The amount of acceleration an object gets from a force is also inversely proportional to its mass. 
		</p>
		<p> 
			These observations were put together succinctly by Newton in the following vector equation, which is the expression of Newton's second law for fixed-mass systems.
			<men xml:id="eq-second-law-f-equal-ma-algebra">
				\vec F = m\vec a.
			</men>
		</p>
		<p>
			Note that this equation does not apply to systems that lose or gain mass during their motion, e.g., rocket (which loses mass) and rain drops (which gain mass). For these situations, we need a more general law, given next.
		</p> 
	</subsection>


	<subsection> <title>(Calculus) Newton's Second Law of Motion </title>
		
		<p>
			<term> Newton's second law of motion </term> states that a <alert> force  on  an object </alert> causes change in its momentum. 
			Quantitatively, the law state that the following relation between the force on an object <m> \vec F </m> and the rate of change of momentum holds true.
			<men xml:id="eq-second-law-momentum">
				\vec F = \dfrac{d\vec p}{dt},
			</men>
			where momentum is defined by
			<men>
				\vec p = m \vec v.
			</men>
			Strictly speaking, <xref ref="eq-second-law-momentum"/> holds true only with respect to special class of observers, called inertial obervers. Inertial observers that have no acceleration with respect to the at-rest center of universe - that is, they are either at rest or moving at constant velocity.
		</p>
		<p>
			If mass is constant, then
			<me>
				\dfrac{d\vec p}{dt} = m\dfrac{d\vec v}{dt} = m\vec a.
			</me>
			Therefore, in this case, Eq. <xref ref="eq-second-law-momentum" /> becomes
			<men xml:id="eq-second-law-f-equal-ma">
				\vec F = m\vec a.
			</men>
		</p>
		
	</subsection>




	<subsection><title>What is mass? </title>
		<p> 
			We use the second law in the form <xref ref="eq-second-law-f-equal-ma" /> <m>(\vec F = m\vec a)</m> to define the property of mass operationally. We apply same force to two different objects and observe their resulting acceleration. The resulting accelerations will be
			<md>
				<mrow> \amp a_1 = \dfrac{F}{m_1}, </mrow>
				<mrow> \amp a_2 = \dfrac{F}{m_2}. </mrow>
			</md>

		</p>
		<p>
			We can divide out <m> F</m> to find that the ratio of their accelerations will be inversely proportional to their masses.
			<men xml:id="eq-a1-to-a1-eq-m2-to-m1">
			 \dfrac{a_1}{a_2} = \dfrac{m_2}{m_1}.
			</men>
		</p>
		<p>
			Suppose we take a reference object and define its mass to be one unit of mass, say <m> 1 \text{ kg}</m>. Then, we perform the aforementioned experiment, i.e., apply an unknown but reproducible force on it. Suppose we find that the acceleration is <m> 4\text{ m/s}^2</m>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			Now, we take an object whose mass we do not know yet. We subject this object to the same force and observe its acceleration. Suppose we find that its acceleration is <m> 6\text{ m/s}^2</m>. Then, Eq. <xref ref="eq-a1-to-a1-eq-m2-to-m1"/> can be used to deduce the mass of this other object.
			<me>
				\dfrac{m_2}{1\text{ kg}}  = \dfrac{4\text{ m/s}^2 }{6\text{ m/s}^2}\Longrightarrow m_2 = 0.5\text{ kg}.
			</me>
		</p>
		<p>
			The example above gives us a process by which, after we choose a reference object of unit mass, we can do experiments to assign mass to all other objects. We call this mass <term> inertial mass </term>.
		</p>

	</subsection>


</section>