<section xml:id="sec-Spectroscopy-of-Hydrogen"><title>Spectroscopy of Hydrogen</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			When a body, such as a blackbody,  is heated, the body emits radiation in all wavelengths.  We say that the black body spectrum is a continuous spectrum. However, when a tube filled with a gas such as hydrogen gas is discharged they emit light of certain wavelengths that is a characteristic of the gas as shown for hydrogen gas in <xref ref="fig-2000px-Emission_spectrum-H"/>.  The spectrum is called a discrete spectrum. <xref ref="tab-balmer-series"/>, called the <term>Balmer Series</term>, lists some wavelengths of light emitted by the hydrogen gas.  The discreteness of the atomic spectra was a mystery in late 1800s and early 1900s.
		</p>
		<figure xml:id="fig-2000px-Emission_spectrum-H">
			<caption>
				The visible part of the discrete spectrum of hydrogen gas.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/modern-physics/2000px-Emission_spectrum-H.png" width="90%"/>
		</figure>

		<table xml:id="tab-balmer-series"><title>Balmer Series of Hydrogen Spectrum</title>
			<tabular halign="center">
				<row header ="yes" bottom ="minor">
					<cell>Spectral line:</cell> <cell>H-<m>\alpha</m></cell> <cell>H-<m>\beta</m></cell>
					<cell>H-<m>\gamma</m></cell> <cell>H-<m>\delta</m></cell> <cell>H-<m>\epsilon</m></cell>
					<cell>H-<m>\zeta</m></cell>
				</row>
				<row>
					<cell>Wavelength (nm)</cell><cell><m>656.3</m></cell><cell><m>486.1</m></cell>
					<cell><m>434.1</m></cell><cell><m>410.2</m></cell><cell><m>397.0</m></cell>
					<cell><m>388.9</m></cell>
				</row>				
			</tabular>
		</table>

 
		<p>
			In 1888 Rydberg was able to guess a formula that could fit the data properly.  For the Balmer series given in the<xref ref="tab-balmer-series"/>, the following formula worked quite well as you can verify by plugging in various values of <m>n</m>.
			<men xml:id="eq-Rydberg-formula">
				\dfrac{1}{\lambda} = R_H \left( \dfrac{1}{2^2} - \dfrac{1}{n^2}\right),\quad\quad n = 3, 4, 5, \cdots, 
			</men>
			where <m>R_H</m> is called the \textbf{Rydberg constant}\index{Rydberg constant} for Hydrogen which has the following value.
			<men xml:id="eq-Rydberg-const-value">
				R_H =  10,973,731.57\:\textrm{m}^{-1}. 
			</men>
			The physical reason for Rydberg formula eluded physicists for a number of years until in 1913 Neils Bohr deduced the Rydberg formula based on rather bold and ad-hoc assumptions, which we will discuss next. 

		</p>
	</introduction>
</section>