<section xml:id="sec-MasslessParticles"><title> Massless Particles</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			Massless particles refer to particle whose rest mass <m>m_0 </m> is zero.
			<men>
				\textrm{Massless particles:    } m_0 = 0.
			</men>
			The momentum of a massless particle will be zero unless it has speed equal to the speed of light.
			<men>
				\vec p = \lim_{m_0\rightarrow 0} \dfrac{m_0 \vec v}{\sqrt{1-v^2/c^2}} = 0\ \ \ (v \ne c).
			</men>
			When <m>v=c</m>, the denominator becomes zero and momentum becomes undefined. In that case, we use  Eq. <xref ref="eq-sq-rel-energy-2"/> to find momentum  of a  massless particle. Thus,
			<men>
				\lim_{m_0\rightarrow 0}\left[ E^2 = p^2 c^2 + m_0^2 c^4 \right]\ \Longrightarrow\ E^2 = p^2 c^2.
			</men>
			Therefore, momentum of a massless particle moving at speed <m>v=c</m>, such as light particle <alert>photon</alert>,  is not zero. Rather, it depends on energy of the particle.
			<men xml:id="eq-sq-rel-energy-3">
				p = \frac{E}{c}. 
			</men>
			The energy of each photon depends on the frequency of the light.  Each photon of light of frequency <m>f</m> has energy equal to <m>hf</m>, where <m>h</m> is Planck constant, whose value is equal to <m>6.627\times 10^{-34}</m> J.s.
			<men xml:id="eq-photon-energy-1">
				E = h f.  
			</men>
			Therefore, momentum a photon will be related to its frequency as
			<men xml:id="eq-photon-momentu-freq">
				p = \dfrac{E}{c} = \dfrac{hf}{c}. 
			</men>
			Writing the ratio of <m>c</m> to <m>f</m> as the wavelength <m>\lambda</m> of light,
			<men>
				\lambda = \dfrac{c}{f},
			</men>
			we obtain an interesting result relating the momentum and wavelength of light.
			<men>
				p\lambda = h.
			</men>


		</p>
	</introduction>

	<exercise xml:id="ex-Decay-of-a-Neutral-Pion-in-Photons"><title>Decay of a Neutral Pion in Photons</title>

		<statement>
			<p>
				A neutral pion, <m>\pi^{0}</m>, decays into two light particles, called photons. The rest mass of neutral pion is <m>135\:\textrm{MeV/c}^2</m>.  That is, if you multiply <m>135\:\textrm{MeV/c}^2</m> by <m>c^2</m> you will get the rest energy in MeV unit. Find the energy and momenta of the two photons released when a neutral pion at rest decays into two photons. 
			</p>
		</statement>
		<hint><p>
			Use formulas in this section.
		</p></hint>
		<answer><p>
			<m> 1.13\times10^{-11}\: \textrm{J}</m>, <m>3.77\times 10^{-20}\:\textrm{kg.m/s}</m>.
		</p></answer>
		<solution>
			<p>
				Let <m>E</m> be the energy of one of the photons. Balancing the energy in the decay reaction we find
				<me>
					2E = 135\:\textrm{MeV}.
				</me>
				Therefore, the energy of each photon is
				<md>
					<mrow>E \amp = 67.5 \:\textrm{MeV} = 67.5 \:\textrm{MeV} \times 10^6\times 1.67\times 10^{-19}\: \textrm{J/MeV}</mrow>
					<mrow> \amp = 1.13\times10^{-11}\: \textrm{J}.</mrow>
				</md>
				The momentum of each photon
				<me>
					p = \frac{E}{c} = \frac{1.13\times10^{-11}\: \textrm{J}}{3.0\times 10^8\:\textrm{m/s}} = 3.77\times 10^{-20}\:\textrm{kg.m/s}.
				</me>				
			</p>
		</solution>
	</exercise>



 

</section>