<section xml:id="Kinetic-Theory-Bootcamp"><title> Kinetic Theory Bootcamp </title>


	<subsection> <title>Pressure in an Ideal Gas</title>

		<problem><title> Root Mean Squared Speed of a Helium Molecule </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Root-Mean-Squared-Speed-of-a-Helium-Molecule"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>

		<problem><title> Pressure from a Stream of Particles Striking on a Wall </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Pressure-from-a-Stream-of-Particles-Striking-on-a-Wall"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>
 
		<problem><title> Pressure from a Stream of Particles Striking on a Wall and Sticking to the Wall </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Pressure-from-a-Stream-of-Particles-Striking-on-a-Wall-and-Sticking"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>


	</subsection>

	<subsection><title>Maxwell's Distribution</title>


		<problem><title> Average Speed and RMS Speed of a Nitrogen Molecule </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Average-Speed-of-a-Nitrogen-Molecule"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>

 		<problem><title> (Calculus) Mean of the Maxwell's Distribution </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Mean-of-the-Maxwells-Distribution"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>

 		<problem><title> (Calculus) Exploring Maxwell's Distribution of Energy of Molecules </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Exploring-Maxwells-Distribution-of-Energy-of-Molecules"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>
 

	</subsection>


	<subsection><title>Mean Free Path</title>

 		<problem><title> Mean Free Path of an Ideal Gas Illustrated </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="example-Mean-Free-Path-of-an-Ideal-Gas-Illustrated"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>

 		<problem><title> Mean Free Path, Mean Free Time, and Intermolecular Distance in Helium Gas </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Mean-Free-Path-HeliumGas"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>

		<problem><title> Variation of Mean Free Path with Pressure, Temperature, Volume, Amount of Gas </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="Variation-of-Mean-Free-Path-with-Pressure-Temperature-Volume-Amount-of-Gas"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>

		<problem><title> (Calculus) Exploring Distribution of Free Lengths </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Exploring-Distribution-of-Free-Lengths"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>

	</subsection>

	<subsection><title> Effusion </title>
		<problem><title> (Calculus) Reduction of Pressure in a Container due to Escaping Molecules by Effusion </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Reduction-of-Pressure-in-a-Container-due-to-Escaping-Molecules-by-Effusion"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>
	</subsection>

 



	<subsection><title> Water Vapor and Humidity</title>

		<problem><title> Partial Pressure of Water Vapor from Humidity </title>
			<p> Follow the link: <xref ref="ex-Partial-Pressure-of-Water-Vapor-from-Humidity"/>.
			</p>
		</problem>


	</subsection>


	<subsection><title> Miscellaneous</title>

		<problem><title> Mean Free Path from Distances Between Successive Collisions of a Molecule </title>
			<statement>
				<p>
					The mean free path is the average distance a molecule travels in-between collisions.  In reality a molecule will travel different distances in-between collisions.  Suppose a molecule  of size 0.3 nm travels the following distances between collisions: 11 nm, 5 nm, 12 nm, 15 nm, 25 nm, 2 nm, 11 nm, 30 nm, 18 nm, 20 nm, 14 nm, 15 nm, 10 nm, 28 nm, 9 nm, 17 nm, 5 nm, 10 nm, 6 nm, 13 nm, 17 nm, 15 nm, 10 nm, 22 nm, 9 nm, 23 nm, 19nm, 4 nm, 15 nm, 12 nm, 10 nm, 16 nm, 11 nm.  
				</p>
				<p>
					(a) Find the mean free path from this data.  
				</p>
				<p>
					(b) What is the standard deviation of space between collisions from the mean free path? 
				</p>
				<p>
					(c) What is the most probable free length? 
				</p>
				<p>
					(d) What is the rms free length? 
				</p>
				<p>
					(e) Supposing,  the temperature of the gas is 200 K and the pressure of the gas is 1 atm, what would be  the diameter of molecules of the gas
				</p>

			</statement>
			<hint> <p> Use a data processing sofware such as Mathematica or Excel or Google Sheets.  </p> </hint>
			<answer> <p>  (a) - (d) See solution, (e) <m>D = 0.66\text{ nm}</m>.  </p> </answer>
			<solution> 
				<p>
					 I typed up the data in Mathematica and used their statistical functions. (a) 14 nm, (b) 6.7 nm, (c) Most common function gave two most-commonly occurring number, 10 nm and 15 nm.  When I drew the histogram I found that 10 nm has more data points clustered around it than 15 nm points.  The most probable length will be 10 nm. (d) 15.4 nm. 
				</p>
				<p>
					(e) Using the formula for the mean free path we get
					<me>
						D = \sqrt{ \frac{k_B T}{\sqrt{2}\pi \lambda p}}.
					</me>
					Now, you can put in the numbers given.
					<me>
						T = 200\ \text{K},\ \ p = 1.013\times 10^5\ \text{Pa}.
					</me>
					This gives <m>D = 0.66\text{ nm}</m>.
				</p>
			</solution>
		</problem>

		<problem><title> Surface Temperature of a Star for Helium Atoms to Escape Gravitational Pull </title>
			<statement>
				<p>
					What should be the maximum temperature of a sun-sized star if Helium atoms cannot escape the gravitational pull of the star? Hint: Equate gravitational escape speed with the rms speed. 
				</p>

			</statement>
			<hint> <p>   </p> </hint>
			<answer> <p>   </p> </answer>
			<solution> 
				<p>
					The escape speed <m>v_e</m> of a body of mass <m>m</m> from a  body of mass <m>M</m> and radius <m>R</m>  is given by equating the kinetic energy to the negative of the potential energy.
					<me>
						\frac{1}{2} m v_e^2  = G_N \frac{M m}{R}.
					</me>
					This gives
					<me>
						v_e = \sqrt{\frac{2G_N M }{R} }.
					</me>
					The root-mean square speed of a molecule when in the environment of temperature <m>T</m> is
					<me>
						v_\text{rms} = \sqrt{\frac{3k_B T}{m}}
					</me>
					Equating the two speeds will give the condition we seek in this problem.
					<me>
						\frac{3k_B T}{m} = \frac{2G_N M }{R}
					</me>
					The temperature will be
					<me>
						T =\frac{2G_N Mm }{3 k_B R}. 
					</me>
					Now, we put in the following numbers.
					<md>
						<mrow> \amp M = 2\times 10^{30}\ \text{kg}\  \  \text{(Mass of Sun)}</mrow>
						<mrow> \amp m = 4\times 10^{-3}\ \text{kg}/6.022\times 10^{23} \  \  \text{(Mass of one He atom)}</mrow>
						<mrow> \amp R = 7.0\times 10^9 \ \text{m}\  \  \text{(Radius of  Sun)}.</mrow>
					</md>
					These give the following for <m>T</m>.
					<me>
						T = 9 \times 10^6 \ \text{K}.
					</me>
					This temperature is much larger than the surface temperature of the Sun.
				</p>
			</solution>
		</problem>







	</subsection>





 

</section>