<section xml:id="Sines-and-Cosines"><title> Sine and Cosine Functions </title>
	<p>
		You have seen sines and cosines in the context of triangles. There, we define them using the sides of a right-angled triangle.
		<sidebyside widths="60% 35%">
			<p>
				<md>
					<mrow> \amp \sin\,\theta = \dfrac{p}{h}, </mrow>
					<mrow> \amp\cos\,\theta = \dfrac{b}{h}. </mrow>>
				</md>
			</p>
			<image source="./images/simple-harmonic-motion/right-angled-triangle.png"/>
 		</sidebyside>
 
 		In a right-angled triangle, the angle can go up to <m> 90^{\circ}</m>. More generally, the angle can be extended to the full <m> 360^{\circ}</m> in the plane, which we have used to indicate direction in a plane. 
 	</p>
 	<p>
 		When we think sines and cosines as functions of <m> \theta</m>, we usually view <m>\theta</m> in radian and not in degrees with <m> 360^{\circ}</m>  equal to <m>2\pi</m> radian. Furthermore, we extend the range of values for <m>\theta</m> to <alert> any real value</alert>, <m>-\infty \lt \theta \lt \infty </m>, and require that sines and cosines be periodic in <m> \theta</m> with period <m> 2 \pi</m>.
 		<md>
			<mrow> \amp \sin\,(\theta + 2\pi m) = \sin\,\theta, \ \ \ (m\text{ any integer}) </mrow>
			<mrow> \amp\cos\,(\theta + 2\pi n) = \cos\,\theta, \ \ \ (n\text{ any integer}) </mrow>>
		</md>
		This periodicity of sine and cosine functions makes them valuable for representing vibrations and waves, such as sound and light.
	</p>
	<figure>
		<caption>
			One period of sine and cosine functions in the range <m>[0,2\pi]</m>. You can extend these plots to any real value of <m>\theta</m> by adding or subtracting interger multiples of <m> 2 \pi</m>. Say you want <m> \sin(20)</m>, you first divide <m> 20  </m> by <m> 2\pi</m>, and throw away the integer part. That gives you <m> 0.183098861837907</m>, which you can multiply by <m> 2\pi</m> to get <m> 1.15  </m>, whose sine will be 0.913 in this plot.
		</caption>

		<image source="./images/simple-harmonic-motion/sine-and-cosine.png" width="80%"/>
	</figure>
 
 	<p>
 		The uniform circular motion in the <m> xy</m> plane has two harmonic motions inside it - one along the <m> x </m> axis and one along the <m> y</m> axis. Here is website that you can play aroud interactively <url href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/cpb0oammx7"> Sine and Cosine in Uniform Motion in a Unit Circle</url> or go to "https://www.desmos.com/calculator/cpb0oammx7".
 	</p>

</section>