<section xml:id="Transverse-Oscillations-of-Beads-on-a-String"><title> Transverse Oscillations of Beads on a String </title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			Imagine placing beads on a taught string and giving the beads a motion perpendicular to the string. The beads appear to move in concert. The motions of beads are coupled through the force of tension in the string. This system provides an important example through which we can see how wave emerges through coupled motion.
		</p>
		<p>
			We will first do a toy example of one bead on a string. Then, we will do two beads on a string. Then <m>N</m> beads on a string.
		</p>
		<!-- <p>
			<xref ref="Motion-of-a-Bead-on-a-Taut-String"/> shows that a single bead on a string acts like a simple harmonic oscillator - the motion is snusoidal with a definite frequency.  
		</p>
		<p>
			<xref ref="Motion-of-Two-Beads-on-a-Taut-String"/> shows that the motions of two beads on a string are coupled with two normal modes. While general motion of a two-bead system may be complicated, the motion of the modes are simple. In each mode both beads oscillate with the frequency of that mode.
		</p> -->
	</introduction>
	<subsection xml:id="Motion-of-a-Bead-on-a-Taut-String">
		<title>Motion of a Bead on a Taut String</title>
		<p>
			Consider a bead of mass <m>m</m> attached in the middle of a taut string of length <m>L</m>, negligible mass, and uniform tension <m>T</m> as illustrated in <xref ref="fig-one-bead-on-a-string"/>. Suppose the bead is pulled by a distance <m> A</m> vertical to the string and let go from rest. We wish to find the displacement and velocity of the bead at an arbitrary instant <m>t</m> assuming small displacement, i.e., <m>A \lt\lt L</m>.
	   </p>
	   <figure xml:id="fig-one-bead-on-a-string">
		   <caption>
				A bead B is attached to a taut string, pulled vertically to the string and let go. The figure shows bead at an arbitrary instant when displacement is <m>y</m>. The tension force <m>T</m> on the bead act from both sides of the string.
		   </caption>
		   <image source="./images/coupled-vibrations/one-bead-on-a-string.png" width="80%"/>
	   </figure>


			<p>
				Let us sketch a figure for bead at an arbitray instant. We will use <m>y</m> coordinate to denote the vertical to the string. Then, we need to figure out the <m>m a_y = F_y</m> of the bead.
			</p>

			<p>
				As shown in the figure, I will use <m>y</m> coordinate to denote the vertical to the string. Then, we need to first set up equation of motion of the bead, which is <m>m a_y = F_y</m>, here.
			</p>
			<p>
				To figure out <m>F_y</m> on the bead in the approximation of small displacement, we note that the <m>y</m> coordinate of the bead is such that <m>y \lt\lt L</m>, and if string makes an angle <m>\theta</m> with the support, we will have
				<me>
					\tan\theta = \frac{y}{L/2} \approx \sin\theta = \cos \angle ABO.
				</me>
				Therefore, we find the following expression for <m>F_y</m>.
				<me>
					F_y = -2 T \cos \angle ABO = - \frac{4T}{L}\, y.
				</me>
				This gives the following for the <m>y</m>-acceleration of the bead.
				<me>
					a_y = - \left( \frac{4T}{mL} \right)\, y.
				</me>
				This equation is an equation of a simple harmonic motion with angular frequency <m>\omega</m> given by
				<me>
					\omega = \sqrt{  \frac{4T}{mL}  },
				</me>
				and the general solution is
				<md>
					<mrow> \amp y(t) = C \cos \omega t + D \sin \omega t, </mrow>
					<mrow> \amp v_y(t) = \omega \left( -C \sin \omega t + D \cos \omega t \right).</mrow>
				</md>
				 At the initial instant we had
				 <me>
					y(0)=A,\ \ \ v_y(0)=0
				 </me>
				Therefore,
				<md>
					<mrow> \amp A = C \times 1 + D \times 0. </mrow>
					<mrow> \amp 0 = \omega \left( -C \times 0 + D \times 1 \right).</mrow>
				</md>
				Therefore, we have <m>C=A</m> and <m>D=0</m>. Hence, the bead in this example has the following displacements and velocity at an arbitrary instant.
				<me>
					y(t) = A \cos \left( \omega t \right);\ \  v_y(t) = -A \omega \sin \left( \omega t \right).
				</me>
							
			</p>

	</subsection>

	<subsection xml:id="Motion-of-Two-Beads-on-a-Taut-String">
		<title>(Calculus) Motion of Two Beads on a Taut String</title>
		<p>
			Now, consider two beads on a string. For simplicity, we will take their masses to be same, <m>m</m>, and place them symmetrically, one at <m>L/3</m> from one end and the other at <m>L/3</m> from the other end, as shown in <xref ref="fig-two-beads-on-a-string"/>
		</p>
		<figure xml:id="fig-two-beads-on-a-string">
			<caption>
				Two beads A and B placed symmetrically on a taut string with tension <m>T</m> shown at an arbitrary instant with vertical displacments <m>y_A</m> and <m>y_B</m>. We study only the vertical motion here.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/coupled-vibrations/two-beads-on-a-string.png" width="80%"/>
		</figure>
		
		<p>
			Rather than study the general motion, we will find only the normal modes of the system in the small displacment approximation, i.e., Assume small displacements, i.e., when <m>|y_A| \lt\lt L</m> and <m>|y_B|\lt\lt L</m>, where <m>y_A</m> and <m>y_B</m> are displacements of the beads.
		</p>

		<p>
			You should show that the <m>y</m> component of net force on the two beads are
			<md>
				<mrow> \amp F_{Ay} = \frac{3T}{L}\left( -2 y_A + y_B\right)</mrow>
				<mrow> \amp F_{By} = \frac{3T}{L}\left( -2 y_B + y_A\right)</mrow>
			</md>
			This gives following for their accelerations.
			<mdn>
				<mrow  xml:id="eq-of-motion-two-beads-on-string-1"> \amp \frac{d^2y_A}{dt^2} = \frac{6T}{mL}\left( - y_A + 0.5 y_B\right)</mrow>
				<mrow  xml:id="eq-of-motion-two-beads-on-string-2"> \amp \frac{d^2y_B}{dt^2} = \frac{6T}{mL}\left( - y_B + 0.5 y_A\right)</mrow>
			</mdn>
			In normal modes, both beads have the frequency of the normal mode. Each bead acts like a simple harmonic oscillator at the frequency of the mode. Let <m>\omega</m> be the frequency of the mode, which we don't know yet - it will be replaced by <m>\omega_1</m> and <m>\omega_2</m> for the two modes. 			
		</p>
		<p>
			How do we find <m>\omega_1</m> and <m>\omega_2</m>? We will just plug in expected behavior of beads in the equations, Eqs. <xref ref="eq-of-motion-two-beads-on-string-1"/> and <xref ref="eq-of-motion-two-beads-on-string-2"/>. That is, we set
			<md>
				<mrow> \amp y_A = A_1 \cos(\omega t) </mrow>
				<mrow> \amp y_B = A_2 \cos(\omega t) </mrow>
			</md>
			This will be their motions if we start the beads in one of the modes, letting then go at rest - once again, of course <m>\omega</m> will be either <m>\omega_1</m> or <m>\omega_2</m>, the angular frequencies of the modes. After plugging these in Eqs. <xref ref="eq-of-motion-two-beads-on-string-1"/> and <xref ref="eq-of-motion-two-beads-on-string-2"/>, we will find these allowed values of <m>\omega</m> and the ratio of <m>A_2</m> to <m>A_1</m>.
		</p>
		<p>
			To simplify writing, I will introduce a scale for angular frequency by 
			<me>
				\omega_0 = \sqrt{ \frac{6T}{mL} },
			</me>
			and 
			<me>
				\tilde\omega = \frac{\omega}{\omega_0}.
			</me>
		</p>
		<p>
			The result is 
			<mdn>
				<mrow  xml:id="eq-normal-modes-two-beads-on-string-1"> \amp  (1-\tilde\omega^2) A_1 = 0.5 A_2 </mrow>
				<mrow  xml:id="eq-normal-modes-two-beads-on-string-2"> \amp (1-\tilde\omega^2) A_2 = 0.5 A_1</mrow>
			</mdn>
			Taking the ratio that cancel out <m>A_1</m> and <m>A_2</m>, we get
			<me>
				(1-\tilde\omega^2)^2 = \left( \frac{1}{2}\right)^2.
			</me>
			This gives two values for <m>\tilde\omega^2</m>, namely,
			<me>
				\tilde\omega_1^2 = \frac{1}{2},\ \ \tilde\omega_2^2 = \frac{3}{2}.
			</me>
			Therefore, angular frequencies of the normal modes are
			<men>
				\omega_1 = \sqrt{ \frac{3T}{mL} },\ \ \omega_2 = 3\sqrt{ \frac{T}{mL} }.
			</men>			
			Putting <m>\tilde\omega_1</m> in Eq. <xref ref="eq-normal-modes-two-beads-on-string-1"/>, we see that the ratio of <m>A_2</m> to <m>A_1</m> is
			<men>
				\left[ \frac{A_2}{A_1}\right]_\text{mode 1} = 1.
			</men>
			Putting <m>\tilde\omega_2</m> in Eq. <xref ref="eq-normal-modes-two-beads-on-string-1"/>, we see that the ratio of <m>A_2</m> to <m>A_1</m> is
			<men>
				\left[ \frac{A_2}{A_1}\right]_\text{mode 2} = -1.
			</men>
			Thus, we have our modes now. the frequencies and displacements of the two modes when started from rest are
			<md>
				<mrow> \amp \omega_1= \sqrt{ \frac{3T}{mL} }, \ \ \ y_A = y_B = A \cos(\omega_1 t)</mrow>
				<mrow> \amp \omega_2= 3\sqrt{ \frac{T}{mL} },\ \ \  y_A = -y_B = A \cos(\omega_2 t)</mrow>
			</md>			

		</p>
		<p>
			We can sketch these normal modes to get the shape of string as the two beads move in one or the other mode. In mode 1, the beads move with the same displacement since <m>y_A=y_B</m>. Therefore, the string will look like a trapezoid at an arbitrary insant. In mode 2, the beads move with opposite displacments since <m>y_A=-y_B</m>. Therefore, the string will have a zig-zag shap.
		</p>


		<figure xml:id="two-beads-on-a-string-modes">
			<caption>
				Two normal modes of two beads on a taut string. In mode 1, the two beads move with the same displacment, and in mode 2, they move in the opposite direction with opposite displacements.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/coupled-vibrations/two-beads-on-a-string-modes.png" width="80%"/>
		</figure>

		

	</subsection>

	<subsection xml:id="N-Beads-on-a-String"><title>(Calculus) N Beads on a String</title>
		<p>
			It is interesting to ask: what will be the normal modes if we have 3, 4, 5, ..., beads on the string. As an illustration, modes of the <m>N=2,3,4</m>> on a taut string system are shown in <xref ref="fig-two-beads-to-four-beads-on-a-string-modes"/>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			You will notice that number of normal modes equals number of these beads and in each mode the ratio of the amplitudes of displacements of different beads must have a particular relation. For instance, in the 3-bead system, we have the following relations between the displacments of the beads.
			<md>
				<mrow> \amp \text{Mode 1: } A_1 = B_1 = C_1. </mrow>
				<mrow> \amp \text{Mode 2: } A_2 = -C_2,\ B_2=0. </mrow>
				<mrow> \amp \text{Mode 3: } A_3 = -\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}B_3 = C_3. </mrow>
			</md>
		</p>
		<!-- <figure xml:id="fig-three-beads-on-a-string-modes">
			<caption>
				The three normal modes of a three beads on a taut string. In mode 1, the three beads move with the same displacment, in mode 2, the two beads on the end move in with opposite displacements with bead in the middle remaining stationary, and in mode 3, all three move so that the string roughly has a shape of a sine function with amplitudes of the beads at the end same, and the bead in the middle has opposite displacement of magnitude <m>\sqrt{2}</m> times those of others.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/coupled-vibrations/three-beads-on-a-string-modes.png" width="80%"/>
		</figure> -->
		<figure xml:id="fig-two-beads-to-four-beads-on-a-string-modes">
			<caption>
				Transverse modes of (a) <m>N=2</m>, (b) <m>N=3</m>, and (c) <m>N=3</m>. In each case <m>\omega_1</m> is the lowest frequency mode.  The points at the nodes, the place where the string crosses the zero displacement, do not oscillate; other points of the string oscillate up and down with the frequency of the corresponding normal mode.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/coupled-vibrations/two-beads-to-four-beads-on-a-string-modes.png" width="100%"/>
		</figure>
		
		<p>
			As you place more and more beads on the string, you can imagine, at some point, we can just say that beads are just continuously placed on the string. This is <m>N\rightarrow\infty</m> limit. In that case, the shapes of normal modes are just piecess of sine function of increasing frequency.
		</p>
		<p>
			The lowest frequency mode has the shape of half cycle of a sine function, the next has the shape of one cycle of a sine function, the next one has <m>\frac{3}{2}</m> cycles, and so on. We can describe the shape of these normal modes by stating displacements at some arbitrary instant, which we denote by functions <m>C_n(x)</m>, for mode <m>n=1, 2, 3, ...</m>. I will state the results here without full calculations since they are involved and you can find them in a book on more advanced books on vibrations and waves.
			<men xml:id="eq-largeN-mode-functions-N-beads-on-string">
				C_n(x) = A_n \sin\left( \dfrac{n\pi x}{L} \right).
			</men>
			Corresponding angular frequencies are 
			<men>
				\omega_n = n \omega_1, \ \text{ with }\ \omega_1 = \pi\dfrac{T},{M}
			</men>
			where <m>M=Nm</m>, the total mass of all beads. The vibrations of string generates waves that move back and forth on the string and are called <term>standing waves</term>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			To get a feel for a large <m>N</m> situation, <xref ref="fig-forty-beads-on-a-string-modes"/> displays four lowest frequency modes of an <m>N=40</m> system. Each mode has no displacement points at the end due to the string being bound there. If you look at the mode corresponding to frequency <m>\omega_2</m>, there is a point in the middle that does not oscillate. This point is called a <term>node</term>. With every successively higher mode, you get one more node in the string's motion.
		</p>
		 
		<figure xml:id="fig-forty-beads-on-a-string-modes">
			<caption>
				Four lowest frequency modes of vibration of a string with <m>N=40</m> beads shown at an arbitrary instant; with time, the string vibrates up and down with the points that fall on horizontal line remaining stationary with time. We see that the masses start to form almost continuous string and their positions fall on the sine function given in Eq. <xref ref="eq-largeN-mode-functions-N-beads-on-string"/>.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/coupled-vibrations/forty-beads-on-a-string-modes.png" width="100%"/>
		</figure>

	</subsection>


</section>