<section xml:id="section-linear-polarizers"><title> Polarizers </title>
	<introduction>
        <p>
        	Natural light such as the light from the Sun is  unpolarized.  It is generally a random mixture of various waves of different polarizations and frequencies. There are devices that act as filter of light and let through light with a particular type of polarization. These devices are called <term> polarizers</term>. 

        </p>
        <p>
        	There are various types of polarizers depending on the polarization of the light that is emitted from the polarizer. For instance, if light emitted is linearly polarized, we call it a <term> linear polarizer </term>  and light emitted is a circularly polarized light we call it a <term> circular polarizer</term>. Linear polarizers are easier to understand and we will mstly look at them. 
        </p>
    </introduction>
    <subsection><title>Malus's Law</title>
        <sidebyside widths="50% 50%">

	        <p>
	        	If you shine a linearly polarized light on a linear polarizer with direction of polarization of light <alert>same</alert> as the the polarization direction of the polarizer, then all of the incident light is trnasmitted through the polarizer. On the other hand, if the direction of polarization of incident light <alert>perpendicular</alert> to the the polarization direction of the polarizer, then all light is blocked.
	        </p> 

	        <figure xml:id="fig-polarization-zero-and-ninety-degrees-demo">
	        	<caption>
	        		  Two polarizers whose axes are perpendicular to each other completely block the light.
	        	</caption>
	        	<image source="./images/wave-description-of-light/polarization-zero-and-ninety-degrees-demo.png" width="90%"/>
	        </figure>
    	</sidebyside>

        <p>
        	Finally, if the   direction of polarization of incident light is some angle <m>\theta</m> to the the polarization direction of the polarizer, then only some of the light is blocked. How much is blocked in this case? To analyze this general case, note that we need to think in terms of electric field to see what is let through and what is blocked. 
        </p>
        <p>
        	A linear polarizer lets through the component of the electric field that is parallel to the axis of the polarizer. Consider a linearly polarized EM wave moving towards positive <m>z</m> axis. Its polarization will be in the <m>xy</m> plane, say at an angle <m>\theta</m> from <m>x</m> axis. This means that the amplitude vector <m>\vec E_0</m> is in this direction. Suppose it is incident on a linear polarizer whose axis is along <m>x</m> axis. Then, the wave on the other side will have amplitude equal to the <m>x</m> component of <m>\vec E_0</m> and direction of <m>x</m> axis, which will be
        	<me>
        		E_{0x} = E_0\,\cos\theta. 
        	</me>
        	Suppose you have the same medium on the two sides of the polarizer, then we can write the ratio of their intensities as
        	<me>
        		\frac{I_\text{out}}{I_\text{in}} = \frac{ \frac{1}{2} \epsilon v E_{0x}^2}{\frac{1}{2} \epsilon vE_0^2} =  \cos^2\theta.
        	</me>
        	That is, outgoing wave will have only <m>\cos^2\theta</m> times the incident intensity.
        	<men>
        		I_\text{out} = I_\text{in}\, \cos^2\theta.
        	</men>
        	This is called <term>Malus's law</term>. How can we test this law? We setup an experiment that produces a linearly polarized light with a known direction of polarization, which is then passed through an identical polarizer whose preferred axis makes an angle <m>\theta</m>  with respect to the polarization direction of the polarized light as shown in <xref ref="fig-polarization-malus-law-set-up"/>. In this setup we calle the first polarizer a polarizer and call the second polarizer an <term> analyzer</term>.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-polarization-malus-law-set-up">
        	<caption>
        		 The polarizer and analyzer in for testing Malus's law.
        	</caption>
        	<image source="./images/wave-description-of-light/polarization-malus-law-set-up.png" width="80%"/>
        </figure>

    </subsection>
    <subsection><title>Linear Polarizers</title>

    	<p>
    		There are some naturally occuring crystals, such as tourmaline, that have dichroic property of preferentially absorbing polarization light. Hence, such a crystal will let through light polarized in the perpendicular direction to the direction of polarization that the crystal absorbs. These crystals introduce some other artefacts such as absorption depending on wavelength also and they are not the primary means we obtain polarized light.
    	</p>

    	<p>
    		A majority of polarizers, such as use in sun glasses, are made from synthetic materials. For instance, in H-sheet Polaroid, clear polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) is stretched along its chains, and then dipped into iodine solution which imbeds into the plastic and arranges along the long hydrocarbon chains, essentially making molecular size wires of iodine.  These Polaroids transmit electromagnetic waves whose polarization is <em>perpendicular to the direction of "iodine wires"</em>. In a sense, these are synthetic dichroic materials, and that is why ther are also referred to as dichroic filters.
    	</p>

	        <figure xml:id="fig-wiregrid-absorbing-polarizer-polaroid-type">
	        	<caption>
	        		   Polarization by absorbing wire grid type material such as the H-sheet Polaroids.
	        	</caption>
	        	<image source="./images/wave-description-of-light/wiregrid-absorbing-polarizer-polaroid-type.png" width="70%"/>
	        </figure>

 
		<p>
			In <xref ref="section-refelection-and-refraction-of-light"/>, we have also seen that if we reflect light at Brewster's angle, then P-wave does not have any reflection but S-wave does have reflection. Therefore, if we reflect an unpolarized light off a surface at the Brewster's angle, then we will get only S-wave in the reflected direction. Now, S-wave is polarized perpendicular to the plane of incidence. This will give light polarized linearly in the direction perpendicular to the incidence plane and parallel to the interface.


		</p>
		<p>
			We will discuss special types of crystals, such as calcite, that have refractive index that depends on the polarization direction of light with respect to a crystal axis.  These crystals are called <term> birefringent crystals</term> This leads to separation of light of different polarizations and hence can  also be used to produce polarized light.
		</p>
		<p>
			By using an appropriate arrangement of linear polarizers, you can obtain polarized light that is polarized in any desired direction in the plane perpendicular to the direction of the wave.  However, each polarizer reduces the intensity of light by blocking off the perpendicular components.
		</p>


	</subsection>


	<subsection><title> Circularly Polarizer</title>
		<p>
			If you look back in <xref ref="subsection-Circular-Polarization"/>, you will find that to produce right circularly polarized light moving in positive <m>z</m> axis, we need to introduce delay of <m>\pi/2</m>  in the phase of the <m>E_y</m> wave relative to the <m>E_x</m> wave. And similarly for the left-circularly polarized light. Thus, we need polarization dependent wave velocity. Recall that wave velocity in a medium is <m>v = c/n</m>. This means we need polarization dependent refractive index. Birefringent materials have just such a property. Therefore,  when a linearly polarized light is sent in appropriate direction and through appropriate thickness of a birefringent crystal, the crystal produces the desired delay. These devices are called <term>retarders</term>.
		</p>
		<p>
			A retarder is constructed to retard the phase of one of the components by a set amount. You can buy full-wave, half-wave and quarter-wave plates. The cause relative retardations of the phase by <m>2\pi\text{ rad}</m>, <m>\pi\text{ rad}</m> and <m>\pi/2\text{ rad}</m> respectively.  Also commonly available are <term>compensators</term> which can be used to produce retardation to a arbitrary degree.
		</p>
		<p>
			The above describes how you can turn a linearly polarized light into a circularly polarized light. If you want to go the other way around, it is much simpler - you just pass the circularly polarized light through a linear polarizer!
		</p>

	</subsection>



</section>