<section xml:id="Conductors-and-Insulators"><title> Conductors and Insulators </title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			You already know that metals are good conductors and plastic is a bad conductor. That is how you are protected from current in wires. Any material that can carry electricity readily is a conductor. For instance, ions in an ionic solution carry electricity between two electrodes, which is how electricity flows in a battery. That makes ionic solution a good conductor. 
		</p>
		<p>
			Different conductors carry electricity in a different way. For instance, metals carry electricity through moving electrons but ionic solutions and plasma carry electricity via ions and other charged particles. 
		</p>

		<!-- <p>
			All materials can be broadly classified as conductors or insulators based on their electrical properties.  The difference comes from the fact that charges flow readily in conductors even with negligible forces on them, while they do not flow in insulators unless you apply a considerable force. At the level of ordinary forces, charges  in insulators appear to be stuck in place. 
		</p> -->
<!-- 		<p>
			Another way to distinguish a conductor from an insulator is to observe what happens when you put some charge on it.  Extra charges on a conductor move about and redistribute on the outside surface of the material as illustrated in <xref ref="fig-charge-on-conductors-versus-on-insulators"/>. This does not happen with insulators.  Instead, when you put extra charge at some place on an insulator, they just sit there attached to the molecules they land on.
		</p>
		<figure xml:id="fig-charge-on-conductors-versus-on-insulators">
			<caption>
				Electric charges on a conductor migrate to the outside surface of a conductor no matter where you put them initially. The charges on an insulator stay put in the location you place them.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/conductors/charge-on-conductors-versus-on-insulators.png" width="50%"/>
		</figure> -->
 
		<sidebyside widths="55% 5% 40%">
			<p>
				One way for distinguishing a conductor from an insulator is to notice what happens when you try to create a potential difference between two points on the object.
				When you do that to a conductor, charges flow and create a current. Ordinarily, this does not happen in an insulator.  
			</p>
			<p> </p>

			<image source="./images/conductors/current-in-conductor-not-in-insulator.png" width="50%"/>
		</sidebyside>
		<p>
			However, if you create enormous potential difference, electrons can flow even in an insulator.
		</p>
		<sidebyside widths="65% 10% 25%">
			<p>
				For instance, even though air is an insulator, electrons flow from ground to the positively charged clouds. Enormous potential difference between the ground and clouds creates very high electric field, which is sufficient to knock electrons off molecules. Once free, electrons are accelerated by the electric field. Moving electrons collide with air molecules, which is responsible for release of light we see as lightning.
			</p>
			<p></p>
			<figure>
				<caption>
					Credits: NOAA.
				</caption>
				<image source="./images/conductors/Calif-willi05-lightning-Credit-NOAA.png" width="50%"/>
			</figure>
		</sidebyside>

		<p>
			The difference in the electrical behavior of conductors and insulators can be traced to the presence of a large number of freely moving charges in conductors and their absence in insulators.  For instance, in copper, which is a good conductor, there is one electron per atom that can freely move in the metal.  
		</p>
		<p>
			On the other hand, in insulators such as a piece of plastic or glass, electrons are tightly bound to molecules, and cannot move macroscopic distances.  Electrons in insulators, however, do move within a molecule, e.g. across a covalent bond.   This causes molecules in an insulator to be polarized if atoms across a bond have different attraction for electrons, or a polarization can be induced if the material is placed in an external electric field.  We shall study the effects of polarization of insulators in the next chapter.  In the present chapter we shall concentrate our efforts at understanding conductors.

		</p>
	</introduction>


	<subsection><title> Electric Field inside a Conductor</title>

		<p>
			The only time charges do not flow in a conductor is when there is no potential difference between any two points of the conductor. This means that a conductor will be in an electrostatic equilibrium when it has same potential everywhere. We say that <alert>a conductor forms a constant potential body</alert>. Since gradient of potential difference is electric field, this implies that inside a conductor in electrostatic equilibrium, electric field is zero.
			<me>
				\text{Conductor in Electrostatic Equilibrium: }\ \ \ \  E_\text{in} = 0.
			</me>
		</p>
		<p>
			When you place some charge on a condutor, such as in <xref ref="fig-charge-on-conductors-versus-on-insulators"/>, initially, charges flow inside the condutor. But, after some time, an <term>electrostatic equilibrium</term> sets in when no more flow occurs. The charges distribute around th conductor in such a manner that electric field by them <alert> cancel at all points of the body of the conductor</alert>! If the outside surface is a spherical surface, they will distribute evenly. But, if outside surface is not spherical, charges will not spread out evenly; charge density will be higher at places that are pointed. 
		</p>
		<figure xml:id="fig-charge-on-conductors-versus-on-insulators">
			<caption>
				Electric charges on a conductor migrate to the outside surface of a conductor no matter where you put them initially. The charges on an insulator stay put in the location you place them.
			</caption>
			<image source="./images/conductors/charge-on-conductors-versus-on-insulators.png" width="50%"/>
		</figure>

		<sidebyside widths="60% 10% 20% 10%">
			<p>
				This observation is used to electrically isolate some space from outside using a Faraday cage.
				You can isolate a volume electrically by using metal chicken wires. In the Faraday cage to the right, there is anulus of space that is isolated.

			</p>
			<p></p>
			<image source="./images/conductors/faraday-cage.png" width="50%"/>
			<p> </p>
		</sidebyside>
	</subsection>

 



</section>