<section xml:id="Operational-Definition-of-Magnetic-Field"><title> Operational Definition of Magnetic Field</title>
	<introduction> 
		<p>
			Based on  the magnetic force law, Eq. <xref ref="eq-mag-force-vector-form" /> we can give the following  <alert>operational definition</alert> of the magnetic field.
		</p>  
		<p>
			<em> Magnetic field <m>B</m> at a point in space is equal to one unit of magnetic field if force on a particle of charge <m>1\text{ C}</m> moving at speed <m>1\text{ m/s}</m> perpendicularly to the field experiences a force of magnitude <m>1\text{ N}</m>. This unit of magnetic field is called <term>Tesla</term>, which is denoted by letter <m>\text{T}</m>.</em>
		</p>
		<p>
			We can write Tesla in terms of fundamental units as <m>\text{kg/A.s}</m>. You can express Tesla in various other ways, such as <m>\text{V.s/m}^2</m>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			It turns out that 1 Tesla is too large a unit for geophysical measurements, and another unit called Gauss (<m>\text{G}</m>) is in common use, where 10,000 Gauss = 1 Tesla.  
			<men>
				1\ \textrm{T} = 10^4\ \textrm{G}.
			</men>
			Earth's magnetic field is approximately <m>0.5\text{ Gauss}</m> while magnetic field of a refrigerator magnet is around <m>1\text{ Tesla}</m>.   Magnetic field used in an Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) machine is around <m>2\text{ Tesla}</m>.  Some typical values of magnetic fields in nature and lab are given in <xref ref="tab-mag-fields"/> so that you can get a feel for the order of magnitude in various situations.  As you can see magnetic field in nature varies over <m>18</m> orders of magnitude, from less than <m>10^{-10}\text{ T}</m> in the interstellar space to more than <m>10^8\text{ T}</m> in neutron stars.

		</p>

			<table xml:id="tab-mag-fields">
				<title>
					Typical Magnetic Fields (from various sources)
				</title>
				<tabular halign="left">
					<row bottom="minor">
						<cell>   </cell> <cell> </cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="minor">
						<cell> Location </cell> <cell>Magnetic Field (<m>\text{T}</m>)</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="minor">
						<cell> Neutron star surface </cell> <cell> <m>10^8</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="minor">
						<cell> Superconducting magnet </cell> <cell> <m>5</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="minor">
						<cell> Small bar magnet </cell> <cell> <m>1</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="minor">
						<cell> Earth's Surface </cell> <cell> <m>0.5 \times 10^{-4}</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="minor">
						<cell> Interstellar space </cell> <cell> <m>10^{-10}</m></cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>

	</introduction>
</section>