<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="electronic-properties" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    
    <title>Electronic Properties of Meterials INPROGRESS</title>

    <p>
        In nature atoms come together to form clumps of various sizes. The very smallest clumps are called molecules. Molecules are basic units of chemical compounds as atoms are basic units of chemical elements. For instance, when two hydrogen atoms come close enough they attract each other and get bound forming the molecule H$_2$ which is the basic unit of hydrogen gas. Same types of atoms can bind in different ways. For instance, a carbon atom can bind one oxygen atom to form carbon monoxide, CO, and also two oxygen atoms to form carbon dioxide, CO$_2$. The particular combinations of atoms for a molecule is governed by the outer-most electrons of  atoms involved. The resulting compounds differ in their chemical and physical properties.
    </p>
    <p>
        Additionally, molecules and atoms can form aggregates of macroscopic size in the form of liquids and solids. Often, solids formed have a repeating structure, called crystals. These repeating structures continue to macroscopic sizes, e.g. in gem stones. However, most commonly, molecules and atoms would form amorphous aggregates, such as sand particles, glass, fluids, etc. Although, amorphous structures are more common, much of our understanding of the electronic properties of materials have come from a systematic study of crystalline solids. In this chapter we will start with a basic description of attraction between atoms that result in molecules. We will then discuss structure of solids.
    </p>
    <!-- Sections -->
    <xi:include href="./electronic-properties-sections/molecules.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./electronic-properties-sections/structure-of-solids.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./electronic-properties-sections/conduction-in-metals.xml" />

    <xi:include href="./electronic-properties-sections/quantum-conduction.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./electronic-properties-sections/band-structure.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./electronic-properties-sections/semiconductors.xml" />

	<xi:include href="./electronic-properties-sections/electronic-properties-bootcamp.xml" />	


</chapter>