<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2020 Samuel J. Ling
*********************************************************************-->


<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <titlepage>

        <author>
            <personname>Samuel J. Ling</personname>
            <department>Department of Physics</department>
            <institution>Truman State University</institution>
            <email>sling@truman.edu</email>
        </author>


        <date><today /></date>

    </titlepage>

    <colophon>
        <copyright>
            <holder>Samuel J. Ling</holder>
            <year>2020</year>
            <minilicense>All Rights Reserved</minilicense>
        </copyright>
    </colophon>


    <biography xml:id="author-bio-TWJ">
        <p>Dr. Samuel J. Ling  received his Master's in Chemistry from Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur, and Ph.D. in Chemistry in 1984 and in Physics in 1989, both from Boston University.</p>

    </biography>


    <dedication xml:id="dedication">
        <p>
            <line>To my students </line>
        </p>
    </dedication>

    <acknowledgement xml:id="acknowledgement">

    <p> I would like to thank PreTeXt production team for creating a really powerful markup processing program.
    </p>

    </acknowledgement>

    <preface xml:id="preface">

        <p>
            This book is written to help students review physics. The book contains a review of main ideas and many solved exercises. Many physics concepts require Calculus for definition. The sections and problems that require Calculus have been marked so that a student who does not need that amount of detail can skip them.
        </p>
        <p> 
            Students can test their understanding quickly by attempting the   Checkpoint exercises, embedded in the concept sections.  Each chapter ends with bootcamp section, which is a collection of problems to further strengthen your ability.
        </p>
        <p> 
            This book should be helpful to anyone preparing for physics contests or medical admissions test or a student wanting a quick review. The presentation also encourages self-learners. May also be useful as a resource for students who are either in a Calculus-based or Algebra-based introductory physics survey course.
        </p>
    

        <attribution>
            <line>Samuel J. Ling</line>
            <line>Kirksville, Missouri 2020</line>
        </attribution>

    </preface>


</frontmatter>