<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="cahp-noninertial-frame" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    
    <title>Noninertial Frames</title>
    <idx>Noninertial Frames</idx>
    <introduction>
    	
        <p>
            So far we have studied motion with respect to inertial observers.  For these observers, Newton's second law of motion takes the familiar form, <m>\vec F = m\vec a</m> for a constant mass particle or in general, <q>\vec F = d\vec p/dt</q>.
        </p>
        <p>
            Observers that have a non-zero acceleration with respect to an inertial observer are called non-inertial. When the second law of motion is written in a non-inertial frame, the equation of motion is modified.  The new equations of motion contain force-like terms that are not present in the inertial frame; these new force-like terms are called fictitious or inertial forces.  We will study these modifications in this chapter.
        </p>
        <p>
            A particularly important application of these modified equations is to the frames fixed to the Earth, also called Earth-based frames. Since Earth is rotating about its axis, all observers on the Earth are accelerating with respect to any fixed inertial frame, say a non-rotating frame fixed to the center of the Earth. This makes all Earth-based frames that rotate about the fixed frame non-inertial.
        </p>
        <p>
            We will see below that Newton's second law of motion in a rotating frame of constant angular velocity with respect to an inertial frame, two inertial forces arise, viz., centrifugal and Coriolis forces.  We will study their implications in some detail in this chapter.  But, first we will study a simple frame that is accelerating in a straight line with respect to an inertial frame and then we study rotating frames.
        </p>

    </introduction>

    	<!-- Sections -->

    <xi:include href="./noninertial-frame-sections/accelerating-frame.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./noninertial-frame-sections/rotating-frame.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./noninertial-frame-sections/earth-frame.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./noninertial-frame-sections/coriolis-force.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./noninertial-frame-sections/noninertial-frame-bootcamp.xml" />


    




    

    


</chapter>