<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="nuclear-physics" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    
    <title>Nuclear Physics INPROGRESS</title>

    <p>
        The study of nucleus began in earnest in 1911 after the discovery of the nucleus by Rutherford, Geiger and Marsden.  Rutherford's experiments proved that the nucleus of an atom is about $10^{-5}$ times smaller in size than the atom and contains all of its positive charge and most of its mass.  Later studies by the husband/wife team Joliet-Curies and by Chadwick showed that the nucleus contained a new type of particle, called neutron, which was neutral in charge but had mass very near the mass of a proton.  Although Henri Becquerel had discovered radioactivity in a naturally occurring substance,  the husband-wife team of Joliet-Curies demonstrated in 1933 that radioactivity occurs also in artificially created nuclei. Enrico Fermi at the University of Chicago, USA, created the first controlled nuclear reactor in 1942 after the discovery of nuclear fission in 1938 by Otto Hahn in Germany that  subsequently led to the making of the atomic bomb by a team of scientists in the US in 1945.  Mark Oliphant was successful in nuclear fusion of hydrogen isotopes in 1932.  The studies on nuclear fusion by Hans Bethe in 1940s and 1950s helped solve the mystery of the source of energy in the Sun and provided better understanding of the nuclear processes in stars and the beginning of the universe.
    </p>
    <!-- Sections -->

    <xi:include href="./nuclear-physics-sections/survey.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./nuclear-physics-sections/radioactivity.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./nuclear-physics-sections/biological-effects.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./nuclear-physics-sections/nuclear-reactions.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./nuclear-physics-sections/nuclear-fission.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./nuclear-physics-sections/nuclear-fusion.xml" />
    <xi:include href="./nuclear-physics-sections/nuclear-physics-bootcamp.xml" />


</chapter>