<section xml:id="Deriving-Keplers-Second-Law"><title> Deriving Kepler's Second Law</title>
	<introduction> <title> (Calculus) Conservation of Angular Momentum in Sun-Planet System</title> 
		<p>
			Kepler's second law is a consequence of the conservation of angular momentum. We look at the motion of one planet and the Sun, a two-body problem interacting with  gravitational form. We will work in the CM frame, where the problem simplifies to the motion of one particle of mass equal to reduced mass.
			<men>
				\mu\dfrac{d^2\vec r}{dt^2} = -G_N \dfrac{\mu\, M}{r^2}\, \hat u,
			</men>
			where <m>\hat u</m> is unit vector pointed towards the origin, the radially inward direction. We can rewrite this as
			<men>
				\dfrac{d(\mu \vec v)}{dt} = -G_N \dfrac{\mu\, M}{r^2}\, \hat u,
			</men>
			where <m> \vec v = d\vec r/ dt	</m>. The left side is the rate of change of momentum. Taking cross product with <m>\vec r</m> on both sides we get
			<men xml:id="eq-rcross-dmuvdt">
				\vec r \times \dfrac{d(\mu \vec v)}{dt} = -G_N \dfrac{\mu\, M}{r^2}\, \vec r \times \hat u.
			</men>			
			The right side is zero since there is <m>180^\circ </m> angle between <m>\vec r</m> and <m>\hat u</m>. By moving <m>\vec r \times </m> inside the <m>d/dt</m> on the left side, we can show that
			<md>
				<mrow> \dfrac{d( \vec r \times \mu  \vec v)}{dt} \amp =\dfrac{d\vec r}{dt} \times \mu \vec v + \vec r \times \dfrac{d(\mu \vec v)}{dt},</mrow>
				<mrow> \amp = \vec v \times \mu \vec v + \vec r \times \dfrac{d(\mu \vec v)}{dt}</mrow>
				<mrow> \amp = 0 + \vec r \times \dfrac{d(\mu \vec v)}{dt}</mrow>
			</md>
			Therefore, Eq. <xref ref="eq-rcross-dmuvdt"/> gives the following equation.
			<men>
				\dfrac{d (\vec r \times \mu  \vec v)}{dt}  = 0.
			</men>
			Since  <m>\vec r \times \mu  \vec v</m> is angular momentum of the relative motion,	this is the statement of conservation of angular momentum.  We can pull <m>\mu</m> out, giving us the following equation obeyed by the trajectory <m>\vec r(t) </m>.
			<men>
				\vec r \times \vec v = \vec c,
			</men>
			where <m>\vec c</m> is a constant vector. Rewrite this as
			<men xml:id="eq-kepler-cons-ang-mom-eqn-to-integrate">
				\vec r \times d\vec r = \vec c\, dt,
			</men>
			and note that the magnitude of <m> \vec r \times d\vec r</m> is the area of the rectangle formed by vectors <m>\vec r </m> and <m>d \vec r</m>, which is twice the area swept by  vector <m>\vec r </m>.
			<men>
				 \vec r \times d\vec r = 2\times \text{Area swept by }\vec r.
			</men>

			<figure xml:id="fig-kepler-cons-ang-mom">
				<caption>
					The position vector <m>\vec r</m> sweeping out half the area given by the magnitude of <m>\vec r \times d\vec r</m>. By conservation of angular momentum, it is shown that the magnitude of the integral <m>\int \vec r \times d\vec r</m> is proportional to time. Therefore, we get the law that radial vector from the Sun to a planet sweeps out equal area in equal time.
				</caption>
				<image source="./images/gravitation/kepler-cons-ang-mom.png" width="45%"/>
			</figure>

			When we integrate Eq. <xref ref="eq-kepler-cons-ang-mom-eqn-to-integrate"/> for any interval <m>t_i</m> to <m> t_f</m>, we find that
			<me>
				\int_{\vec r(t_i)}^{\vec r(f)} \vec r \times d\vec r = \vec c (t_f - t_i),
			</me>
			where the left side is twice the area swept by vector <m>\vec r</m> as shown in <xref ref="fig-kepler-cons-ang-mom"/>. Writing the magnitudes only with <m>\Delta A</m> for area swept and <m>\Delta t</m> for time interval, we will get
			<me>
				\dfrac{\Delta A}{\Delta t} = c/2,\text{  a constant.} 
			</me>
			That is, the radial position vector of <m>\mu</m> sweeps out equal area in equal time. Since mass of Sun is much greater than most planets, particle <m>\mu</m> can be replaced by the planet alone, which is the observation made by Kepler in his second law of planetary motion. By Newton's analysis, we get more than Kepler's law - we see the precise variables we should look at when we are computing the area swept.	Additionally, we see that Kepler's second law is a consequence of cnservation of angular momentum. 	
		</p>
	</introduction>
</section>